顾问! 我找到他了!
Counselor! I've got him!
下来!你下来!
Down! You come down!
马上下来吧!
Down for good!
抱歉这么早打扰您.
Forgive this early intrusion.
你好啊
How are you?
我一直都很仰慕您. 很荣幸见到您.
I am a great admirer of yours. Honored to meet you.
可以么?
May l?
我可以用下打字机么, 先生?
Can I use your typewriter, sir?
你的手臂，放松.
Your arm, please. Relax it.
- 年龄? - 43.
- Your age? - 43.
那么，您的下一部作品是什么?
So, what are you cooking up?
又是一部没劲的戏?
Another film without hope?
－第一次治疗么? －是啊
- First time taking the cure? - Yes.
深呼吸
Take a deep breath.
请进
Come in.
- 对不起.我待会儿再来吧 - 没关系，进来吧
- I'm sorry. I'll come back later. - No, do come in.
吸气
Breathe in.
深吸气
Deeper.
早上好啊...我能吸烟么?
Good morning... May I smoke?
咳嗽
Cough.
呼气
Breathe in.
- 您读过了吧 - 是的
- You've already read it? - Yes.
吐气
Breathe.
那么...您怎么看?
And... what do you think?
嗯，我记了东西，一会儿给你看
Well, I made some notes, but we'll talk later.
你身体有点疲劳 可以穿上衣服了
Your system is a bit worn out. You may get dressed now.
这姑娘看起来还行啊，是美国人吧
Nice looking girl. American, right?
你够专业的了
You've got some fine merchandise there.
这个治疗对您的病很有帮助， 你会很快恢复的
This treatment will do you good, you'll see.
护士，300毫升清水
Nurse. 300 ml of holy water,
空腹15分钟后，吃3 片
3 doses to be taken at 1 5 minute intervals, on an empty stomach.
- 隔一天清洗一次 - 什么时间了?
- Mud bath every other day... - What time is it?
泥疗后十分钟，在处方上的药水里泡十分钟
After the mud bath, ten minutes in the mineral water as prescribed...
我在温泉那等你 好，谢谢你了
- I'll wait for you at the spring. - Yes, thank you.
先生!
Sir!
您的杯子
Sir, your glass.
在这呢
Over here.
您想聊聊那部电影么? 那太好啊
You want to talk about the film? - Yes, of course.
好的.那就是说， 你想让制作人也看到我的意见么
Fine. Just tell me if you'd like the producer to see my report.
放心，我不会给您添麻烦的
Frankly, I wouldn't want to be the one to cause you any trouble.
别担心 让你来就是要听你的意见么
No, don't worry. I'm the one who called you in.
首先，我觉得这部片子
On first reading it's evident
缺少矛盾冲突， 或者说铺垫的还不够
that the film lacks a problematic, or a philosophical premise...
要坐下聊吗?
Would you like to sit down?
...整体上这部片子没有连贯性
...making the film a series of gratuitous episodes,
影片重点放在非现实主义
perhaps amusing for their ambiguous realism.
会让人觉得主题还不够突出
One wonders what the authors are trying to say...
这是一部让人联想的片子呢? 或者是惊栗?
Are they trying to make us think? To scare us?
影片的开端，就显得缺乏灵感
From the start, the action reveals a poverty of poetic inspiration.
希望您别介意，让我来解释一下原因
Forgive me, but this might be the definitive proof
影片的手法有点落后
that cinema is 50 years behind all other arts.
主题显得有些没有意义
The subject doesn't even have the merits
这部片子，确实需要改改
of an 'avant garde' film, but it has all the shortcomings.
看看我的笔记，也许会有点帮助
Here, my notes. I doubt they will be helpful.
我还是有点不敢相信您会考虑我的意见
It's still a mystery that you'd think of me
从合作的角度来讲，老实说 我觉得您不会考虑
for a collaboration that, frankly, I don't think can work.
不，绝对不.相反，这对我很有帮助
No, no. On the contrary. You'll be most helpful.
你看看，这部片子... 我真的很想拍出来
You see, the film... I really want to make this film.
我推迟两个星期拍就是因为...
I postponed the shoot for two weeks because...
马责柏塔! 你说什么?
Mezzabotta! Pardon me.
马责柏塔! 马里奥! 你也来了?
Mezzabotta! Mario! You're here too?
贵度!
Guido!
你这是怎么了?
What happened to you!
嘿，老贵度，最近怎么样?
Hey, big Guido, how are you?
你也开始长白头发了，老了啊!
You've sprouted quite a few white hairs, old Snaporaz!
你又喝这个? 对你不好的!
Are you drinking that stuff? It's bad for you.
他们说我的肝...唉 你这是治什么呢?
They said my liver is, well... And you, what's your treatment?
等一下...珂劳迪亚!
Just a second... Gloria!
你女儿.已经成人了啊 哦，她不是我女儿
- Your daughter. She's all grown up. - No, she's not my daughter.
残忍的蜜蜂，吸食了花朵美丽的生命
Cruel bees, sucking all the life from these poor flowers.
亲爱的，这是我的朋友... 对不起，我这鞋...
- Darling, this is my friend... - I'm sorry. My shoes...
珂劳迪亚，珂劳迪亚 莫仁 你好
Gloria. Gloria Morin. - Nice to meet you.
你好
Fine, thank you.
我认识你，你的爸爸常常提起你
I know all about you. Pupi always, always tells me.
我们还因为评论你的上一部片子大吵一架呢
We even had a big fight when I was very critical of your last film.
是啊.我们真的很喜欢看
That's not true. You liked it a lot.
去喝点东西吧，走
Let's go for a drink. Let's go.
你一个人来得么? 你夫人呢?
And you, are you here alone? And your wife?
是啊，一个人来的 一个人多好
- Yes, I'm alone. - Better that way...
哈哈，还是这样好啊
Well, I mean, better in general...
你听说我和蒂娜的事了吧 谁是蒂娜?
You heard about Tina and me? - Tina?
我们在等着宣誓
We're waiting for an annulment.
所以我们都来了. 我们已经订婚了
That's why we're here together. We're engaged.
恭喜你们!
Congratulations.
哈哈，老贵度.你在忙什么呢?
Well, big Guido. What are you working on? Something good?
我在想找一个世外桃源让我静一静
Sure is the ideal place to do some thinking.
丹米尔，我就是作者，这位小姐... 对不起，改怎么称呼你?
Daumier, the author, Miss... Pardon me, what is your name?
珂劳迪亚 莫仁
- Gloria. - Gloria Morin.
见到你很高兴! 我非常欣赏您的作品
Nice to meet you. I am a big admirer of yours.
过奖了!
I'm flattered.
你是演员么? 我好像在那见过你的照片
Are you an actress? Did I see your photo somewhere?
演员.是的, 嗯...
An actress. Yes, well...
我确实想过. 而且野心还不小
I have ambitions in that area. Actually enormous ambitions,
不过也只是想想而已
but that's all, for the moment.
她可是哲学毕业的哦
She's got a degree in philosophy.
见到你是我的荣幸.马里奥 很高兴见到你
Allow me. Mario Mezzabotta. - Nice to meet you.
我还没拿到文凭. 我正在写篇论文，有点不一样的论文
I don't have a degree. I'm doing my thesis. It's a bit different.
在写什么? 是很难的那种
- And the subject? - A difficult one.
是探讨男性在现代生活当中的孤独
The loneliness of modern man in contemporary theater.
听起来不错，对吧，专家
Interesting subject. Right, Professor?
要反映点什么呢? 是反复无常的幻觉么
And what is the meaning of the capricious apparitions
来体现女性存在的意义
of the girl of the spring?
很纯洁的题材 主题很有亲和力
An offer of purity? Of warmth to the protagonist?
所有我见过的题材中 很明显，这是最糟的了
Of all your story's overabundant symbols, this is the worst...
希望她写不出来，最好是写不出来!
She didn't make it. Better that way.
别废话了，你怎么样? 还好吧
- Yack! How are you? - Not too bad.
有人认识你么? 我想不是吧
- Did anybody recognize you? - I don't think so.
这些包都是你的么?
You brought all that luggage?
有5个箱子 衣服就有好多
It's just five suitcases. Gowns occupy so much space.
我带来一个...给你看看 全是你带来的?
I brought one... you'll see. Did you get it all?
珂尔拉，这里晚上很安静的 什么活动都没有
Carla, it's quiet here at night. There's nothing going on.
这么时髦的地方 一定有节目的
But it's a fashionable spa. There must be some fashion shows,
有些酒吧很热闹的啊，酒店里就有
some trendy clubs, even at our hotel.
你去看看了么? 是啊
Have you been behaving? - Yes, yes.
可是...我的酒店里已经满了
Actually... I couldn't get you a room in my hotel,
而且酒店里的人都认识我
and besides it's full of people who know me.
这样吧，我来安排个地方 找个好点的...
So, I found someplace else. A perfect hotel...
那倒不错，可是... 为什么要这样?
Very pretty, you know... - But why?
这小子是谁? 斯古么?呵呵
- And how's this guy? - Sgulp? Great.
你脸色不太好，怎么了?
You look a little pale. How come?
就是这，我说的就是这
See, the hotel is right here.
斯格诺拉，房客
Signora, guests!
我就说么，也很一般...
See. Like I told you. It's not...
这里也很安静啊.你不是饿了么
but it's very quiet. If you're hungry,
我去叫点三明治的来
I'll get them to bring a couple of sandwiches.
这给我感觉不太好 没有拉，这也不错
It feels a little sad here. - No, it's typical!
我当然饿了. 你都吃过午餐了，我还没呢
Besides I'm hungry. You had lunch, but I didn't.
你好，先生
Hello, Sir.
单人房间舒服么
How's the solitaire coming along?
什么都有的，有单独的卧室和洗手间
Everything's ready, the room, the bathroom.
放心休息吧 斯格诺拉会象在家一样舒服的
Rest assured. Signora will feel at home.
好的，谢谢你.有什么吃的么?
Yes, thank you. You wouldn't have anything ready for lunch?
休息室里就有 就在这边
- The restroom, please? - It's over there.
我自己去就可以了
I'll see to it personally.
真不好意思. 我的手好脏啊
Trains, such horrible things. They leave your hands so black.
我来了你不高兴么 当然高兴
Are you happy I'm here? - Yes.
是一点点还是很开心 特别的开心
- Really happy or a little happy? - Very happy.
嗯，不错
Hmm. Smack!
你笑起来真甜
Mm, what a nice smell!
贵度，这绒面一定会很皱起来的
Guido, I thought this black velvet was going to wrinkle.
是吗?好，好 不，不会皱的
- Really? Good, good. - But no. Not a wrinkle.
坐三个小时都不会皱的
Even after a three-hour trip.
你还没说喜不喜欢呢 觉得怎么样?
You didn't even tell me you like it. Do you like it?
你穿上更漂亮了
Such a beautiful lady!
她戴着很优雅
So refined. That thing she has on her head...
这是什么? 舒服么?
What is it? Ploosh?
舒服，舒服，哦，还不错
- Plush, plush. - Ah, ploosh.
我就是要找这个呢 真是踏破铁鞋呀
I looked around for it like crazy. I was quite desperate.
你真了解我啊 当珂尔拉后悔的时候...
But you know me. When Carla makes up her mind...
好了，好了
- Snarp! - Sgulp!
我上周读了一个唐那得的故事
I read a good Donald Duck last week...
有一只恐龙
There was a dinosaur...
她就在这，我的宝贝屁屁 正经点，一只恐龙...
- Here she is, my sweet-buns. - Be good, a dinosaur...
贵度正经点 你想知道什么
Guido be good. What do you want to do now?
你肯定会出席么? 当然了，为什么问这个?
Are you sure you've been behaving? - Sure, why?
随便吧，我已经饿了 哦，我的结婚戒指
Anyway, now sweet-buns is hungry. Oh, my wedding ring.
听着，贵度. 你可答应过我的...
Listen, Guido. That little thing you promised me...
答应什么了?
What little thing?
我打赌她一定要说她丈夫的事了
Now I bet she brings up her husband again.
你不觉得么? 看着吧!老家伙
You don't think so? You'll see, old Snaporaz.
可怜的，她看起来一点也不开心
My poor Luigi doesn't seem happy at all.
你看，我丈夫一点都不自信
You see, my husband is not the confident type.
他只是有点沮丧
He gets depressed.
他一点都不笨，还很聪明的
He's not stupid, you know. He's actually very clever...
呜啊，这儿好热
It's so hot here!
他对罗马的历史了如指掌
He knows all of Roman history by heart.
他只需要一点点的帮助
He just needs a push.
他在石油公司上班，只有那么一点点薪水
He's still working at the fuel company, same salary.
是么
Really?
快把钱包给我 别弄花了
Be good and put down my purse. You'll break it.
我很喜欢这个钱包 是他给我的
I love that little purse. He gave it to me.
你怎么不帮他找份别的工作
Why don't you find him a job?
你交际广 而且也答应过我的啊
You know so many people. You've promised it so many times.
我曾经梦到过
I even had a dream about it.
梦见你真的给他找了份工作
I dreamed that you did find him a job,
可是他疯了 还把我们一起杀了
but he'd lost his mind and killed us both.
啊? 你和我?
- Who? - You and me!
在那里呢?
Know where we were?
就是在我给你买领带的地方
In that little street, Via della Croce, where I bought you
你老婆也给你买过一条的， 还记得么?
the same tie your wife did. Do you remember?
我真想知道 你戴的是谁给你买的
And I never knew if you were wearing hers or mine.
梦里我们躺在床上， 相互依偎着，一丝不挂的
We were there on a cot, in each other's arms, naked.
然后他进来把我俩都杀了
And he came in and he killed us both with a broom!
把窗帘放下 对
- Draw the blinds more. - Yes.
可以了.现在去走廊散散步吧
That's it. Now go into the corridor for a minute,
然后假装你走错房间了
then pretend you've come to the wrong room
看到一个陌生人
and found a stranger.
哦!就是这样 我们从没这样过
Oh, that's good. We've never done this one.
站在那别动 让我再看看你
Hold it there. Let me look at you.
不，不是这样，你需要再补补的桩，再多一点
No. No. Your make-up needs to be more, more...
多点什么? 像个荡妇一样!
- More what? - More like a slut!
来我帮你画画
Give me your eyeliner.
这眼影不错 对，就要这样
- Nice lampshade. - Yes, yes.
这灯好漂亮，我也想要一个放在我家 别动
- I'd like one for my place. - Don't move.
这酒店叫什么来着?
What is this hotel called?
旅行宾馆
The Railway Hotel.
我要写信给我丈夫
I want to write to my husband so he'll send me
让他马上给我快递. 他写的信很得体的
an express letter right away. He writes such nice letters.
我会让你看看的 好，别动
I'll let you read them. - Fine, but keep still...
做个诱惑的表情
Make a slutty face.
走到走廊那
Go out in the corridor.
这就是我需要演的那部分么 是的
- So, it's a part I have to play. - Yes.
你怎么看我? 你的演员么?
Who do you think I am? One of your actresses?
你不觉得我可以变成他们一样么
You don't think I could be one of them?
那可不是我想要的生活
Not me. I wouldn't want to lead that life.
我喜欢一直在家待着
I like staying home.
好，快出去吧.我要假装睡觉了
Go on, get out. I'm sleeping now.
告诉我.你是不是很喜欢我这样呀
Tell me. If I were really to do something like this,
你有点嫉妒了吧
would you be jealous?
为什么?真的么?
Why? Would you really?
也许吧
Who knows?
你需要点什么 不，我只是走错房间了
- May I get you something? - No, I just came out on a whim.
要我给你放点水洗澡么 不用了，我只是...
- Would you like me to run you a bath? - No, I was just...
要喝点水么? 不了，谢谢你
- A glass of water, perhaps? - No, thank you.
碰到谁了? 说什么呢?
What did she want? What did she say?
是主人，她要给我杯水
The owner, she wanted to give me a glass of water.
过来点，来
Come here. Come.
拿开床单
Open up the sheet.
贵度，你喜欢我么? 当然了
- Guido, do you love me a little? - Yes, yes.
是你么，妈妈?
Is that you, Mama?
好难过，儿子，好伤心
So many tears, my son, so many tears.
爸爸，等等!别走
Papa, wait! Don't go.
我们还没谈完啊
We talked so little.
爸爸，我有好多事不明白
Listen Papa, I have so many questions.
我还不能马上回答你
I cannot answer them yet.
这的屋顶好低，你看看
See the ceiling here? It's so low.
我想要个高点的 这个太糟了，儿子，我不喜欢
I would have liked it higher. It's ugly, my son, ugly.
我想换一换了 你能帮我么?
I would have liked it different. Couldn't you take care of it?
你画画不错，能不能帮我...
You used to draw so well. I'd like...
哦，卡门多，本不该麻烦他的
Oh, the Commendatore, he shouldn't have bothered.
嗨 我现在有点时间
- Hello. - Respects. He's got very little time.
嗨
Hi.
我的儿子怎么样了?
How is he doing, this son of mine?
小心啊，不要让他骗了你
Careful. Don't let him move you.
他不是很好?怎么了?
He isn't doing well? How come?
我知道这很难过，不应该犯这样的错的
It is so hard, realizing that one has made such huge mistakes.
可是我...
But l...
你妈妈给你做了点心
Mother prepared you a little something.
奶酪和桃子
A little cheese and two peaches.
不用担心我了
Don't worry about me.
好吧，虽然这里有点冷清
Sure, this place gets a little lonely,
你妈妈会每天来陪我的
but your mother comes every day.
她给我做伴 帮我打点一切
She keeps me company, you know. And keeps everything in order.
应该客气点的
A little decorum is always necessary.
我们就是这么长大的
That's how we were brought up.
和你妻子，陆纱也是这样的么?
And with your wife, Luisa -- all fine?
是啊，陆纱
Yes. Luisa...
你们俩在一起真好. 再见了，我的儿子
You two together have been my joy. Goodbye, son...
这是什么地方? 你喜欢吗?
What is this place? Do you like it here?
我还没布置好呢
I haven't figured it out yet.
这里会变得很温馨的
But it's going much better.
首先，看这...
At first, you see, at first...
贵度! 我的宝贝儿子 让我看看你还需要点什么?
Guido! I do my best. What more can I do?
可怜的贵度，你肯定精疲力尽了 要不咱们回家吧
Poor Guido, you must be tired. Shall we go home?
我是陆纱，你的老婆啊 不记得我了么?
I'm Luisa, your wife. Don't you recognize me?
你想什么呢?
What are you thinking about?
嗨! 你好!!
- Hello. - Hello.
下午好!
Good afternoon.
贵度!过两天， 你就会适应的
Guido! In a few days, I'll get you an introduction
很快你就可以得到建议了
so you can get all the advice you need.
很奥妙的雕塑吧
Nice mystical figure. Right?
我做了三个老人
I brought you the three old men.
一个俄国人 还有一个退役的将军
One is a Russian, another is a retired general...
那个老人?
What old men?
就是演父亲的那个啊
The ones for the role of the Father.
挡着我，瑟萨芮诺
Cover me, Cesarino...
往那跑呢. 布冯
Come here, buffoon.
你好吗? 看到你太好了，我的老朋友
How are you? So nice to see you, Super Tarzan!
我叫了你6遍了 哦，我知道了
- I called you six times. - Yes, yes I know.
珂劳迪亚的剧本怎样了 嗯?
- It's about Claudia's script. - So?
我本想寄过去给你的
I thought about mailing it to you.
其实我已经寄出去了 是么?
In fact, I've already mailed it. - Really?
你看起来还不错 怎么不回去继续演戏?
You've still got your looks. Why don't you go back to acting?
我整晚都在设想关于宇宙飞船的剧本
I was up all night with an idea for the spaceship.
我们一起来研究一下如何
Why don't we make the upper story...
别碰我的胳膊，我不喜欢这样，穿上夹克
Conocchia, don't take my arm! I hate it! And wear a jacket!
和你说话还要穿衣服...
Now I need to wear a jacket to talk to you...
你好啊，旅途如何?
How are you? How was your trip?
很好，有一个小时了
Good. It's been an hour...
好炫目的布景，太美了
What a blinding vision! Beautiful!
是么? 嗯
- Really? - Yes.
你总是夸奖我
You're always telling me I'm 'bellissima'
但是还没说过关于我的戏
but you never tell me about my part.
拍出来效果如何? 当然好了，所以还是让你继续演
How was my screen test? - Great, or you wouldn't be here.
他们说我该更丰满些，多吃点通心粉
They told me I have to look motherly and eat a lot of pasta.
再胖点，是这样么?
I should gain six pounds. Is this all?
看看，你知道的都比我多了
See? You already know more than I do.
你是作者，你该知道的比我多阿
You are the author. You should be telling me something.
这位女士该如何呢? 什么?
- What should this lady do? - What?
阿哥思尼!
Agostini!
打扰一下 酒店已经可以了
I don't want to bother you. The hotel is grand,
威士忌，太好了 我还有3个问题
the whisky, excellent. But I have three questions.
好好，等一下 啊，什么?
Yes, yes, later. What is it? Ah, yes, yes. Pardon me.
阿哥思尼，我们应该...
Agostini, we should...
我不太想和他谈
I just didn't feel like talking to that guy.
珂劳迪亚全世界都有档期
Claudia is getting offers from all over the world.
我可不想让她一直等 给她点什么
I can't keep her waiting. Give her something.
你有剧本么 随便什么，或者什么设想
Do you have a script, a few pages, an idea?
珂劳迪亚知道这主意不错吧
Does Claudia realize that this might be a great part?
这个角色她最合适 我跟她解释一下
Perhaps the best she's ever played? I'll explain...
我从一个朋友的角度说，你会失去她的
I'm telling you as a friend, you're gonna lose her.
你想看看老人么? 你怎么了?我们已经准备...
- You want to see the old men or not? - Are you crazy? We're ready...
什么? 老人啊
What? - The old men.
在那里? 这啊
- Where are they? - Here.
斯格诺拉打电话来，说不想住那个酒店了
Signora Carla called. She doesn't want to stay in that hotel.
很恶心.她是对的 我该怎么办?带她过来?
It's ugly. She's right. - What can I do? Bring her here?
我会去叫老人过来
I'll call the old men.
我想给你介绍一下我妻子
Sorry, I wanted to introduce you to my little wife.
见到你好激动啊!
Thrilled.
她有时候也写作的.是个女性杂志的专栏作家
She writes too. She's a columnist for some ladies' magazines.
她有点问题想讨教一下
She's got a few questions for you.
我的读者们疯狂的追求浪漫
My readers go crazy for romance.
跟我说说你的浪漫史吧
Could you tell me something about your love life?
他们在这呢! 跟多特里打个招呼吧
Here they are. Say hello to the Dottore.
坐下，将军你也坐下
Step down. You too, General.
您的年龄?
- How old are you? - 70.
您呢?
- And you? - 64.
您?
- And you? - 68.
他们还不够老啊
They aren't old enough.
还不够?这家伙可都快不行的人了啊
What? This one has one foot in the grave.
下次我会带来三个特别的 您要得那种悲剧型的
Next time I'll get three corpses. You asked for a pathetic type...
保证让你一看就想哭的那种
This one makes you wanna cry the minute you see him.
你好，卡门多
Hello, Commendatore.
你跪下后，我该怎么办?
If you kneel, what do I do?
快起来，别伤了你自己 你好吗?小贵度
Get up or you'll hurt yourself. How are you, little Guido?
你好，卡门多
Hello, Commendatore.
我们做直升机来的，吵死了
We took a helicopter. This one screamed the whole way.
游泳池在那里?
Where's the swimming pool?
我们还没入住呢，别吵
We haven't even checked in. Shut up!
怎么样，治疗有效么? 有的
Has the treatment helped? - Yes.
这里感觉好点了么? 这是什么?
- Feeling better? Here. - What is it?
纪念币
Just a token.
你总是带礼物来
- You're always giving me presents. - It's just like mine.
干吗包起来呢
It doesn't need winding.
是块表，一块表，快来看
A watch! A little watch, everyone!
那么，你的思路该清晰些了吧 是啊，我觉得是
- So, are your ideas any clearer now? - Yes, I really think so.
我们找到美国人了...
We've got the Americans...
我见过她的证件，已经52岁了
I've seen her passport. She's 52 years old?
哦，还不是很老嘛
Ah, she's a little girl.
晚上好，西诺拉
Good evening, signora.
这是谁啊，亲爱的
And who are you, darling?
导演先生，我还有个小问题
Mr. Director, another little question...
他想知道天主教和马克思之主义之间的联系
He wants to know the relationship between Catholicism and Marxism.
谢谢你，我知道了
Thank you, I got it.
你想知道我的政治倾向
You want to know about my political affiliation.
作为一个诚实的人，所有象我这样的意大利人
As an honest man, and all of you ltalians are,
都可以回答你的问题
you should be able to answer me.
意大利人天生就都信仰天主教么?
Is ltaly an essentially Catholic country?
是啊，就是这样的
Yes, it is!
吃你的冰激凌，别多嘴
You shut up and eat your ice-cream.
这是飞船的初步构想
It's the estimate for the spaceship.
我等会儿好好和你谈谈，面对面的
I need to talk to you later, face to face,
我一点思绪也没有了 感觉一点也不好
I'm at the end of my rope. This is a madhouse!
那我们还是以后再谈好了 你的胆库醇还高么?
Fine, we'll discuss it later. What was that about your cholesterol?
一个伟大的作家. 菲茨杰拉德（英国小说家）
...only one great writer. The early Fitzgerald.
后来他的作品变得豪放，有些兽性的现实主义
Then his writing became an orgy of pragmatism or brutal realism.
呵呵，比较矛盾的问题
What does Left or Right mean?
你这么个乐天派居然相信这些
You're such an optimist to believe that in a world
在这混沌的世界，也有人自认清高的
this confused and chaotic there are people so lucid
这些都是矛盾的象征
as to belong exclusively to the Left or the Right.
这就是美国人的思维
The Americans have this new theory about cholesterol...
你的冰淇淋还不错吧 嗯，好吃
- Is your ice-cream good? - Very good.
能不能明确告诉我，她有多少出戏可演
Could you say approximately how many scenes she'll be in?
什么?
What?
戏么? 5场
- How many scenes? - Five.
只有5场么?
Only five.
或许6，7个
Maybe six, or even seven.
晚上好
Good evening.
Hi，贵度
Hi, Guido.
大使在看夫人呢
The Ambassador's got his eye on signora.
怎么了?
So?
我想您应该知道这些 好的，我已经知道了
- I thought you'd want to know. - Good, now I know.
我帮您约她跳舞怎样? 去问问她吧
- Do you want me to ask her to dance? - Yes, ask her.
亲爱的朋友们，事实是...
Dear friends there's only one truth...
我是多么渴望知道，我得角色是什么
But I am so anxious to know, to understand my character.
电影开始前，我需要酝酿一下角色
I need to coexist with my character for a while before shooting...
夫人说想知道她能演什么
The lady says she needs to know her character.
我要加深对她的了解 她的想法，要不我会演不好的
I need to get inside her skin, her ideas, or I'll fail.
作家还没根您解释你的角色么?
Hasn't the Maestro explained the part yet?
还没呢 真抱歉，亲爱的女士
- No. - I am sorry, dear lady.
我还不知道那么多 我只是个制作人
I don't have such information. I'm only the producer.
贵度，你知道我的 对，您并不了解电影那些事
Guido, isn't it true that I know nothing? - Right. Not a thing.
可以休息3天了
And now three days of rest.
春天的樱桃，过来我们一起享受一下这春色
They look like glass. The first cherries of spring.
祝贺贵度么
Thanks. And for Guido?
马里奥，好好祝贺他
Mario Mezzabotta, all 200 pounds of him.
我们散散步如何?
Shall we take a little walk?
我知道...你认为我注定失败
I know... Naturally, you think I've lost it.
嗯
Yes.
我比她大30岁，可这不是问题.
- I'm 30 years her senior. So what? - It's all right.
我也许有点愚蠢，老的有点笨了 在她身上花费点，没什么
I may be the fool, the old imbecile, the one who foots the bill. So what?
能不能说点建设性的意见
Could you create something important, beautiful and real on a commission?
比如，就当教皇让你这么做
For instance, if the Pope asked you?
好吧，好吧，我会考虑的 失陪一下
Yes, yes. I'll think about it. Excuse me.
听着，我并不怀疑自己
Listen, I'm not deluding myself.
她可能只是为了钱和我在一起的
Maybe she's only with me for the money.
事实上就是这样的
Actually, that's certainly it.
可我从来没这么爱过一个人
But I've never felt closer to anybody in my life.
看看她，美貌，迷人，又那么惹人疼爱
Just look at her. She's pretty, charming, intelligent.
她是女人中的女人.难道只是钱这么简单?
She has it all. Only for the money?
现在有钱的年轻人很多啊
But there are so many rich young men around these days, loads of them.
很明显，她很在乎你
It's clear. She cares for you.
事实上，她从未让我觉得不舒服
Right. And she hasn't tried to pressure me.
我可是个理性的人
I made up my mind rationally.
她也从未要求取代我妻子
The poor thing has never even mentioned my wife,
我的家庭，一点怨言都没有
my family, never a reproach.
你们怎么认识的?
How did you meet her?
在伦敦，她和我女儿读一个学校的
In London. She was in school with my daughter.
您结婚了多久了?
How many years have you been married?
很久了，有31年了
Many. 31.
聊聊你的妻子...
And your wife...
我老婆一点都不喜欢她，对她很凶
My wife took it really badly. She hates her.
格洛里亚，这种事总是要露馅的
While Gloria, poor thing, is fond of her.
你是不是认为我很蠢
So spell it out. I am a fool!
我们定下档期吧，什么日子
There must be a shooting schedule. Dates.
我们可以不用德国人的 还有其他选择
Otherwise we're off to Germany. We have other offers.
你会支持我到最后么?
Will you be leaving me in the dark 'til the end?
你看起来一点也不自信
You look like a little snail.
那里不自信了?
- What is a little snail? - Une petite escargot.
我已经看到希望了
Can you hear the voice of the springs?
罗马人说这是“希望之泉”
The Romans used to call it 'Happy Waters.'
玛雅，我们来吧
Maya, let's entertain these bores.
可以嘛?
May l?
准备好了么，玛雅? 我拿的是什么啊
Are you ready, Maya? What am I holding?
有绒毛的钱包啊
A velvet purse.
我说的是里面 一个白色手帕
- And inside? - A white handkerchief.
红的吧
A red one.
没有药吧 哦不，没有药的
- No drugs, I hope. - No, it's aspirin.
一个钱包 里面有钱嘛?
- A purse. - Is there any money in it?
2，725 里拉
2,725 lire.
这位女士在想什么呢?
And this lady here. What is she thinking?
我希望她可别想歪了
No dirty thoughts, I hope.
也许真的在想事呢
Just think about something.
那在想什么呢?
About what?
也许是讨你喜欢呢 你在想么
Whatever you like. Are you thinking?
是啊
Yes.
我真想再多活上100年
I'd like to live another 1 00 years.
祝你好运
Best of luck!
这位漂亮的女士戴的是什么?
And what is in this pretty lady's head?
我说是
Let me be.
我想起一个人么
May I think about someone?
说吧，小姐
Yes. Go ahead, Lady!
我不好意思说
Forget about it. I'm ashamed.
为什么?
What about?
我真的想起一个人
Can I really think of a person?
我不想让你知道
I'd be afraid to have my thoughts read.
别怕，亲爱的 告诉我没什么的
Don't you worry darling, no risk there.
我们还是走吧 有点冷了
Would you like to leave? It's cold.
亲一下换一个耳光 对么?
A little kiss and a big slap. Is that right?
亲爱的女士们先生们， 你们一定在想，“这个骗子”
Ladies and gentlemen, you're thinking, 'What a trickster.'
对不起，其实这里并没有什么玄机
Well, sorry to disappoint you, but there's no trick.
这只是个巧合而已
And it isn't just a coincidence.
同时也证明了异性并不一定相吸
It's an exceptional example of magnetic fields and telepathy.
我这就是我要告诉玛雅小姐的
I transmit your thoughts to Mlle. Maya.
你，真的认为可以骗过我们?
You! Do you believe you can hide your thoughts?
请离她远点 别再坚持了
Please, leave her alone. Don't insist.
有些想法很奇怪的
Thoughts are sacred.
其实这只是个游戏而已
See, it's all a game.
玛雅，你准备好了么?
Maya, are you ready?
等一下，请告诉我先生们在想什么
Just a moment, could we know what you gentlemen are thinking?
那么就问问您吧
You for instance.
您在想什么?
What are you thinking?
还有什么?我的大导演.
What else? My director. My cross and my delight.
你好吗? 不错，你呢
- How are you? - Fine. And you?
有些日子没见到你了...好几年拉!
It has been quite a while... years!
哦，真是，天啊
Unfortunately yes, my dear.
等等，你现在很出名了嘛
Just a moment. You're famous now.
少来了 快点告诉我这里面有什么名堂
Cut it out. Just tell me what's your trick?
嗯，半真半假吧
Well, it's partly a trick, but part of it is real.
我并不完全明白，但就是象这样的 能变成别的什么么?
I don't know how, but it happens. - Can you transmit anything?
什么都行，除非她失手
Anything. Except for her to get lost.
想试试看么? 好啊，等等
- Do you want to try? - Yes. Wait.
我跟你打赌，这肯定行的
I bet now, with you, it won't work.
我不太明白.可以再来一次...
I don't understand. I can't repeat...
阿撒...尼撒...摩挲? 是这样嘛?
Asa... nisi... masa? Is this right?
对的? 就是这样
- Right? - Yes.
那究竟什么意思呢?
But what does it mean?
贵度，过来这 你在那呢?
Guido, come here! Where are you?
别被宠坏了哦!太奇妙了
Don't be spoiled! What a wonder!
我还不想洗澡，真的不想...
I don't want to take a bath, I don't want to...
是你过来...还是让我去抓你?
Come here... Iet me catch you?
我知道这流氓想干什么
I know what that rascal wants.
他想她的宝贝背着他吧
He wants to be carried by his sweetheart,
是他吧，那个猛男
doesn't he, the strapping lad.
来，过来
Come here. Come here.
他从来不想洗药浴，淘气的孩子
He never wants to take the wine bath, the naughty boy.
难道你不想治好，将来变成真正的男人么?
Don't you know that if you do you'll grow into a strong man?
贵度 是胆小鬼，贵度 是胆小鬼
Guido is scared! Guido is scared!
恶棍是要被诅咒的
The Devil and damnation!
奶奶，奶奶
Granny, granny!
今年的木头都受潮了
The wood is all wet this year.
这猫每天四处乱窜，跟你爷爷一个样
This prowling cat is just like your grandfather.
整天乱跑，只有吃饭的时候才回来
Always on the prowl and only comes in for food.
真可耻，快睡觉吧!
Shame on you! Go to bed.
上次我就让他吃了闭门羹
Last time I slammed the door in his face
整整两天不让他回来
and left him outside for two days.
嫁给他真实委屈我了!
I could have married again and found a handsome man,
我的条件完全可以找个比他更好的
rest assured, better than your grandfather.
我当年真是太笨了
What an idiot I am!
要是我选了第一个丈夫的话，无论在天堂
I thought that if I took another husband, my first husband,
还是在地狱，我都会比现在幸福的
whether in heaven or hell, wouldn't have waited.
安静点，睡觉吧，你们这帮小鬼
Be quiet! Go to bed, children!
奶奶，珂劳迪亚身上湿了
Nanny, Claudio wet himself!
这是干什么呢?快睡觉去 你也是，快去
What are you doing? Go to sleep. You too, sleep.
小贵度, 快进被子里去 外面冷，别乱动
Little Guido, get under the covers. It's cold. Be still.
你祈祷了么?
Did you say your prayers?
看你这漂亮的小卷毛，太美了
Aren't you a beautiful sticky bun? The most beautiful!
我也要亲一下
Give me a kiss, too.
你最喜欢的是我嘛? 对不对呀?
Who do you love best? Me? Is that right?
你骗不了我的
You can't fool me.
小心我打你屁股
I'm going to give you a spanking.
你可逃不过我的眼睛的
I can tell when you're pretending.
小鬼，好好睡
Sleep tight, little creatures.
合上眼
Close your eyes.
贵度，别睡了好么
Guido, don't close your eyes tonight!
今天晚上怪怪的，你不会害怕，是吧?
It's the night the portrait's eyes move. You're not scared, are you?
你必须要安静!
You must be quiet!
古丝那叔叔将会窥探那个角落，并且发现那个宝藏的!
Uncle Agostino will look into the corner and find the treasure!
别害怕!贵度!我们会有钱的!
Don't be afraid, Guido! We'll be rich!
你记得那个咒语嘛?阿撒...尼撒摩挲... 阿撒 尼撒摩挲...嘘!!
Do you remember the spell? Asa Nisi Masa... Asa Nisi Masa... sh!
先生，有几个从罗马打来的 电话找您，我猜是您的妻子
Sir, you got two or three calls from Rome. Your wife, I think.
好吧，让我听吧.
Fine. Get me the line.
基诺，让这位先生听电话. 好的.
- Gino, get the gentleman the line. - All right.
给您!晚安，先生! 晚安!
- This is for you. Good night, sir. - Good night.
玛赛勒，那个从罗马打来的电话?很快啊.
Marcella, that call from Rome, quickly.
这没什么?
No, I'm not offended.
让我不舒服的只有一件事
There's only one thing that offends me.
你认识我.不可能
You know me. No.
我原谅了他所有的一切.
I forgive him everything.
我们少聊一会吧.
Let's have a little chat.
挨着我坐一下!
Sit beside me for a moment.
不行，我要睡觉了，我很累，并且我在等一个电话.
No, I'm going to bed. I'm very tired and waiting for a call.
你想要点吗?
Would you like some?
不，谢谢.我觉得头很痛!
No, thank you. I have such a headache.
把你的手给我.
Give me your hands.
不，还是坐下吧!
No, sit down.
我有的左手有治疗的功效.
I have a healing fluid in my left hand.
当我腹痛的时候，我就用它止痛.
I put it on my belly when it aches.
脱掉你的帽子.
Take off your hat.
好些了吗?
Is it any better?
嗯，好一些了.
Yes, maybe.
你为什么那样看着我?
Why do you look at me that way?
哦，不要说我漂亮.那会让我会觉得是一种侮辱.
Oh, don't say I'm beautiful. You make it sound insulting.
你没事吧?
What's with you?
我不知道.
I don't know.
我觉得我的生活和工作中 一切决定都是错误的.
I feel I made all the wrong decisions in my life and in my work.
不要折磨我了，快说吧
Tell me, why do you enjoy torturing me?
折磨你?
Torturing you?
像个朋友一样的说真话吧!
Talk to me as you would to an old friend.
我应该多了解了解导演
I need to feel close to my director.
你看了我上一部片子么，在贝尔格莱德的那部
Did you see my last movie, the one shot in Belgrade?
我的角色是个妇人 显的有些苍老的女人
My character was a woman marked by the injuries of time,
但是风韵犹存
yet still desirable...
来点 “神秘感” 虽然我并不知道那是什么
- Play "Mystification". - I don't know it.
但是可以演...
But yes...
太刺激了...这角色...
What a character... this woman...
可是...
But...
一个让人感到安逸和被爱着感觉
In whom people find protection and love.
我就是这样一个人 生活中和她一样的
I am this character. I am like her in life and love.
所以我感到很孤独
That's why I'm so lonely.
我总是原谅男人所作的不对...
And I have always forgiven everything in the man...
因为我爱他们.
the men, I love.
先生，罗马的电话 谢谢
- Sir, Rome on the line. - Thank you.
我很恶毒，贪欲
I am very sensual. Wicked, too!
对，对，就是这样的感觉! 我马上就回来
Yes, yes, you're very close. I'll be right back.
罗马的电话通了，您可以通话了
Rome on the line. You may speak.
您好，是的.
Hello, yes!
你要找陆纱? 对
- Do you want Luisa? - Yes.
你个禽兽，你不害臊嘛? 我是 罗瑟拉
Feeling guilty, you beast? This is Rossella.
嗨，罗瑟拉，你好嘛 陆纱在找我
Hi, Rossella. How are you? Luisa was looking for me.
你这次又跑那去了? 治疗?真会编...
Where were you this time? Your rest cure? What an excuse...
陆纱来了
Here comes Luisa.
贵度，我打过电话给你，你在那?
Guido, I called you twice. Where were you?
我刚知道，真对不起
I know. I'm sorry.
我在工厂这，在开工
I was up in the production office. We're working.
你还好么?
How are you?
还不错...那治疗进展如何?
Not bad... And the treatment?
有点作用了.
Is it helping?
也许吧，但是，你知道 我还不能好好休息
Perhaps. But, you know, I can't really rest.
你呢?在忙什么? 过得好么?
And you? What are you doing? Having fun?
还是老样子.我和罗瑟拉在一起，还有 泰裕恩科.他们正要走呢
The usual. I'm with Rossella, Tilde, Enrico. They were about to leave.
那你过得好么? 找到你的红颜知己了么
But are you having a good time? Did you meet anybody?
好难啊.我觉得不太可能了
Hardly. It's a terrible bore.
但是为了工作，只能这样了
But for my work, it's better this way.
晚安吧，贵度 晚安
- Good night, Guido. - 'Night.
你没和谁约会吧? 你总是这样一个人么?
You've met no one you know? Are you always alone?
就是这样的
Of course.
真的么?
Really?
陆纱，你来我这散散心吧
Luisa, why don't you come visit?
来住几天. 况且过来也很方便
Just a short stay. It's easy to get here.
你什么时候开始拍摄， 现在很无聊么?
When are you going to start shooting, you bore?
我还不知道. 还是让我和陆纱说吧
I don't know. Let me talk to Luisa, please.
那，我真的可以去么? 你想让我去么?
So, should I come? Do you want me to?
我当然想了
If you'd like to.
你还可以带个朋友一起来
You could even bring a friend.
这样好么?
But would it make you happy?
当然好了，要不我也不会让你过来
Of course, or I wouldn't ask you.
先生，您还要继续通话么? 不了
- Sir, are you staying on? - No.
我该什么时候过去呢?
When should I come?
随时都可以
Whenever it's good for you.
小心咯，我真的要来了
Careful, I'll come.
亲爱的，那还犹豫什么，来吧
Darling, I wouldn't have asked.
我很想... 迫不及待了，晚安吧
I'd love it... So long, and good night.
再见了，远方的先生.晚安
Bye, Mr. Alienated. Good night.
晚安，贵度
Night, Guido.
晚安，绅士
Monsieur Guido, my agent thought...
等一下，夫人.我刚进办公室
Just a second, madam. I am going to step into the office so...
天啊! 这可是我最喜欢的
- Shit! - It's in my best interest.
明天早上我们再仔细谈吧 好吗?
Tomorrow morning we'll discuss everything. All right?
主要结构：10,000
Beams for the central structure:. 1 0,000.
地上的木板：260
Planks for steps: 260.
晚上
'Evening.
您需要点什么呀?
Do you need something?
没什么，谢谢了. 不打扰您工作了
No, thanks. Go on with your work.
你们这支摄影组还很有凝聚力么
What a well-behaved production team.
嗨
Hi.
哦，嗨 依蕾莫拉
Oh, hi Eleonora.
钢材：2，350
2,350. Corrugated iron.
听着，多特拉，正好你也在
Listen, Dottore, since you're here.
我打电话那德国人打电话，可她已经走了
I called the pensione about the German, but she's gone.
你必须找到她 她现在和一个马戏团在巴黎
- You must find her. - She's in Paris with a circus.
真的嘛?
Really?
我该怎么作呢?
What should I do?
这是我的荣幸，多特里
What an honor, Dottore.
让你捉歼在床了
You've caught me with my pants down!
听着贵度. 农场的事...是这样的...
Listen Guido. About the farm... there's that...
看这，这是那里啊?
Ah, here. Where's this place?
连地址都没写，什么都没有
It doesn't even have a note about the address, nothing!
这是属于王子的
It's in the Prince's estate.
谁在里面那? 是我的侄女么
- Who's in here? - My little nieces.
依瓦和蒂娜
Eva and Dina.
- 晚上 -
'Evening.
来，让导演看看你
C'mon. Let him take a look at you.
也许他会给你一点戏呢
Perhaps he'll give you a little part.
很高兴见到你 荣幸之至
- Nice to meet you. - My pleasure.
你从那里来的?
Where are you from?
的里雅斯特 [意大利东北部港市] 意大利万岁!
- Trieste. - Hurray for ltaly!
你布置的还不错呀
You've got a nice set up here, don't you?
跟他聊聊我的表弟
Tell him about my cousin.
贵度.这个是我的表弟 6尺高了
Guido. This one's cousin is six feet tall.
你该认识认识她 也许可以安排个角色给她呢
You should see her. She might be good for the movie.
这个么...像个恶女啊
This one... you she-devil...
真的.她和我站在床上一样高那
It's true. She's tall like me standing on the bed.
哦?
See?
她获得过两次尼龙袜小姐呢
She's twice been voted Miss Nylon Stockings.
贵度在这么?我进来了
Is Guido in there? I'm coming in.
睡吧，克诺其雅，快睡觉 明早见
Sleep, Conocchia, sleep. I'll see you tomorrow.
我能问你个问题么?
May I ask you a question?
说吧
Go ahead.
我的朋友说... 你拍不了爱情片
My friend here says... you can't make a love story.
住嘴 她说得很对
- Shut up! - She's right.
要我明早叫你起来么?
Should I wake you up in the morning, Guido?
不了，谢谢你
No, thanks.
我们头从来没抓到过我们偷懒
Our commander will never catch us unprepared.
这些工作组从来不休息的
This production crew never sleeps!
头好痛.我这是吃什么了?
Such a splitting headache. What did I eat?
虽然有时候他们也胡闹 可是本质却不坏
They're always horsing around, but they're good guys.
你还需要什么，贵都 这是你的新创意么
Do you need anything, Guido? Is it a new idea?
有事要跟我说么
Do you have something to tell me?
不了，谢谢你，没什么
No, thank you, no.
快回去睡觉吧 我不需要什么了
Go back to bed. I don't need anything.
说吧，什么都行 真的没有了，谢谢，晚安!
- Anything at all. - No, thank you. Good night.
睡你个头
Good night my ass!
这怎么能让人睡啊 根本就睡不着
Who can sleep here? How can I get any sleep?
可卡尼亚，别生气啊
Conocchia, calm down.
快饶了我吧，我干这行30多年了
Allow me. I have been in this business for 30 years,
我拍电影得时候你还小呢
I've worked on movies you couldn't begin to imagine
我什么没经历过啊
and I have never been afraid of anything!
你胡乱发什么牢骚 老家伙!
What are you shouting for, you crazy old man!
看，你终于说出来了，我老了
There, you've said it now. Old.
这才是你的心里话 可卡尼亚老了啊
Finally you've spat it out. Conocchia is old.
在这看什么? 快进去
What do you want? Get back inside.
你们总是蒙骗我 总是让我什么都不知道
You always keep me in the dark. I never know what to do.
对我指指点点得 我也不想烦你的
When to talk or when to shut up. I don't want to bother you.
我跟本就不在乎你的电影
I don't want to know what this movie is about.
你还想保密?随便你 好了，快睡觉吧
- You want to keep it a secret? Go ahead. - Please, go back to bed.
可是我还是象以前一样帮助你
But if I'm to help you out, as I've always done,
你以前不是很高兴么 跟我分享一下好不好
and you were so happy then, you must tell me something!
提醒提醒我，不要再和那些法国女人在一起...
Tell me: get rid of the French woman...
我总是梦想着有搜宇宙飞船 让我自由得飞翔
this is how I want the spaceship... tell me: go hang yourself,
能不能跟我说说话啊
but do tell me something.
你变了，贵度，我的老朋友
You've changed so much, Guido my friend.
你这是干什么? 别激动，你还是以前的那个你
What are you doing now? Crying? Aren't you ashamed?
我明天就走了 不干了
I'll be leaving tomorrow. I'm quitting.
我不耽误你了 你放手干吧
I don't want to be in your way. You need some young blood.
但是小心点，你可不是以前的你了
Just be careful. You're not the man you used to be, either.
这是批评还是鼓励啊?
A crisis of inspiration?
如果是不及格你怎么办?
And what if it weren't a passing one, my dear?
也许只是那个老头子骗你呢?
What if it's the final collapse of a filthy liar
没用的笨蛋，闭嘴
with no flair or talent? Sgulp!
就当什么也没发生吧
Let's say you are purity itself.
可他到底是什么意思啊
But what the hell does it mean to be really honest?
你听到法卡丝奥说什么了?
Didn't you hear what the Falcaccio said?
是时候放下包袱了 轻松的，清白的，放弃吧
"It's time to set all the symbols aside, the echoing of purity, innocence, escape."
那你到底需要什么呢
What is it you want then?
可能就是这个吧
Yes, this could be it.
城里有个博物馆 你是看门人的女儿吧
There's a museum in the town, and you, the guard's daughter,
从童话里走出来的仙女么
grew up surrounded by images of ancient beauty...
你说的对了
You're right.
我要永远留在这了
I've come to stay forever.
我要重新整理一下 我要纯净的....
I want to create order, I want to cleanse...
喂?
Hello?
他们在找你 是旅游宾馆打过来的
They're asking for you from the Railway Hotel.
好的，转过来吧
Fine. I'll take it.
喂?你是...?喂?
Hello? Who's that? Hello?
贵度，我好怕 我有点水土不服了
Guido, I feel dreadful. The mineral water made me sick.
我发烧了. 快来，过来陪陪我
I have a temperature. Come. Come here, immediately.
已经很晚了 不行，我明天去吧
At this time of night? I can't. I'll come tomorrow.
来嘛!
Come.
这小可怜，她很想见你的
The poor thing, if you only knew how she was asking for you.
这是冰块
Here's the ice.
她烧的厉害.起码38度了 好了，这里有我
- She's melting. She's got at least 1 04. - Yes, fine. Just go now.
要我把豌豆拿过来么? 豌豆?
- Should I bring the peas? - What peas?
刚才她昏昏沉沉的时候说要豌豆
When she was delirious she asked for peas. It's a good sign.
不用了，算了吧
No, just forget about it.
需要什么，就叫我吧 好的，谢谢了
- If you need anything, let us know. - Yes, thanks.
卡尔拉，你怎么会突然发高烧呢?
Carla, is this the first time you've run such a high fever so suddenly?
不.这是怎么了?
No. It shoots up over nothing.
我会没事的 我丈夫都习惯了
Then it goes away. My husband is used to it.
他从来都不怕
It doesn't scare him
躺在床上，不要起来.
No, don't get up. Stay under the covers.
我很热，也很渴.等一下，喝点水吧，在.
- I'm so hot. I'm thirsty. - Wait, I'll give it to you. Here.
慢慢喝水，不然你会全身浮肿的.
Drink slowly or you'll get all bloated!
现在是白天还是晚上?你说什么啊?
- Is it day or night? - What are you talking about?
现在是下午四点.
It's four o'clock in the afternoon.
听好，我们现在在等医生，听听它怎么说.
Listen, now we'll wait for the doctor and see what he has to say.
最好给你丈夫发个电报.
It wouldn't be a bad idea to send your husband a telegram.
我们不能对此全全负责.对，他应该知道.
We can't take full responsibility for this. Yes, he ought to know.
不，我不想和你分开.如果他来了，他要带我带走的.
No, I don't want it to be over. If he comes, he'll take me away.
并且我已经带来这么多漂亮的衣服.
And I have bought so many nice little dresses.
慢点喝啊?
Why did you gorge on all that water?
有病的人才那样，你生病了嘛?
That's for sick people. Are you sick?
你总是准备好要狼吞虎咽一顿.
You're always ready when there's something to gorge on.
我也是没有办法啊?你总是丢下我一个人.
What else should I do? You're always leaving me here alone.
我两年前就想好了我的遗愿.
I drafted my will two years ago.
其实，立了遗愿也不会那么快就死掉的
Anyway, it's not like you die sooner just because you make a will.
你知道的，我还有一个哥哥，和一个妹妹.
You see, I have a brother and a sister too,
但是，我希望我的丈夫继承那个公寓.
but I'd like the apartment to go to my husband.
它是我的，但是我可怜的丈夫没有它可怎么办啊?
It's mine, but how would the poor thing manage with out it...
即使他再婚.
even if he does get remarried?
哦，这些可恶的被单!
Ah, these sheets!
听我说，告诉我那真相，真相，你知道我说什么么?
Listen, tell me the truth, the truth, you hear?
你为什么和我在一起?
Why do you stay with me?
我明天要怎么和那个教父说呢?
What can I tell the Cardinal tomorrow?
是的，我读过了你的制片人的大纲.
Yes, I did read the little synopsis your producer sent us.
它真的是很生动有趣!我可是实话实说
It's very interesting. From a factual point of view though,
角色之间的摩擦很生动
the meeting between the protagonist
可是王子什么的就不太现实了
and a prince of the church could not happen during a mud treatment
象你说的 很抱歉，事实上不太现实
as you describe it. I'm sorry but it's absolutely not feasible.
一个高级教士拥有他自已的私人房间.
A high prelate has his own private room.
是这样，可是我再找一个非传统的背景.
True, but I was looking for an unconventional setting.
你指什么?
What do you mean?
这个主角得到了一个天主教徒得抚养，并且....
The protagonist received a Catholic upbringing and...
早上好. 阁下，这位是安瑟米
- Good morning. - Monsignor, this is Guido Anselmi.
你好.你一定是导演吧.
Nice to meet you. You must be the director.
是的.
Yes.
这部电影得主题是关于宗教吗?
Is the subject of this film a religious one?
嗯，是的.
Well, yes, in a manner of speaking.
象我说过得，这个主角得到了一个天主教徒的抚养，
As I was saying, the protagonist had a Catholic upbringing,
象每个人一样，他的个性也很复杂.
Iike all of us, for that matter. So, he has certain complexes,
他已经不能再压抑.
certain needs he can no longer repress.
教会的人帮助他
And a prince of the church appears to him like the depositary of a truth
神魂颠倒的他已经不能承受太多了
that he can no longer accept although it still fascinates him.
所以，他寻找帮助 或者只是些理解
So, he seeks contact, some help, perhaps a flash of understanding.
大马士哥（叙利亚首府）的索尔么?
Saul in Damascus, right?
我们不都是和他一样么
Don't we all harbor such hopes?
这构思也许有点肤浅，粗俗，可是我...
I do realize the idea might sound a bit superficial, gothic if you want...
不，真不是这样的
No, no, that's not it.
电影院不可能总是放映那几个单调的题材的
I don't believe cinema lends itself well to certain topics.
你可别混淆视听，赎渎世间的爱情啊
You mix sacred and profane love too casually.
难道不是这样么? 也许是吧
Isn't that so? - Maybe.
你这反映也太强烈了吧
Yours is a great responsibility.
你可能成为前车之鉴啊
You can either corrupt or educate thousands of souls.
他可是很崇高的
His Eminence will listen to you all the same.
你可以问问他的意见
You can ask him some questions.
请允许我介绍导演
Allow me to introduce you to the director.
请，请坐
Please, do sit down.
从头说说 我不会介意的
Please pardon the intrusion, Your Eminence. I wouldn't presume,
我的制作人总是说让我来请教你 他是对的
But my producer is restless, perhaps he's right,
他还坚持说我...
and he insisted that l...
结婚了么? 是啊
- Are you married? - Yes.
有孩子么 还没有呢
- Any children? - Yes. I mean, no.
年龄?
- How old are you? - 43.
听到鸟的歌声了么 你说什么?
- Do you hear this singing bird? - Pardon?
知道这歌叫什么名字么
- Do you know what it's called? - No.
这是 狄莫尼亚
It's called Diomedeo.
狄莫尼亚的死造就了一个不朽的神话
The legend has it that when Diomedes died,
鸟儿们飞到一起 在他的墓碑前守候
all these little birds gathered and accompanied him to his grave
唱着哀曲
singing a funeral lamentation.
听....它们像是在哭泣
Hear? It sounds like wailing.
贵都贵都，我们去看看吧
Guido, Guido let's go see the Saraghina.
来
Coming.
萨拉纪娜，跳段伦巴
Saraghina, dance the Rumba.
在这
Here.
丢人，太丢人了...
Shame on you, shame on you...
这次饶不了你了!
It's a mortal sin, it's a mortal sin...
这不是真的吧
I don't believe it, it can't be true...
看着你妈妈，看着她的眼镜
Look at your mother, look at her!
妈妈! 别过来
- Mother. - Stop there.
天啊，我好难过 你让我好伤心
Oh God, I'm so ashamed, so ashamed and hurt!
总之，在他的有生之年里
But above all, during his whole life and in any place where he lived,
这种感觉一直没有逝去 不愿意和任何女人接触
the pious Luigi most abhorred any talk or dealing with women,
就是这样，不管见到谁
whose presence he avoided in such a way that whoever
很自然的就想回避
saw him thought he had a natural dislike of them...
跪下!
Get down!
你不知道 萨拉迪诺 是个恶魔么
Don't you know that Saraghina is the devil?
我不知道的 真的不知道
No, I didn't. I really did not.
这个情节有什么意义么?
So, what does it mean?
这个角色刺激了这个孩子的童年
It's a character inspired by your childhood memories.
这是良心的谴责么
No connection with a real critical conscience.
不，除非你想挑起争执
No, if you really want to make a polemical piece
你并不了解意大利的天主教，
about the ltalian Catholic consciousness, you would need
你应该更深入的了解他们的文化
a much higher degree of culture
而且要无比的深入和透彻的了解
as well as inexorable logic and clarity.
请原谅我，可是... 你的天真注定要失败的
Forgive me, but... your naivete is a serious failing.
你的思乡情节太浓了
Your little memories, bathed in nostalgia,
这让人觉得你非常脆弱
your inoffensive and fundamentally sentimental evocations
你也只能这样了
are all the expressions of an accomplice...
“什么?” 和共产主义者?
"How?" said the parish priest, "With a communist?"
看看，他都没说是一个 “人”
See? He didn't say: 'a man'.
天地良心
Catholic conscience?
想想恺撒时期的政治家们
Just think what Suetonious was at the time of the Caesars!
你的初衷本是谴责，可是结果呢?
No, your intention was to denounce, but you end up
却像个同僚一样
supporting it like an accomplice.
我就说吧，这很不清晰
See? What confusion... what ambiguity!
我可爱的医生啊，你让我又爱又恨
Dear Doctor, I'm very angry with you!
你已经不需要我了
But you don't need me anymore.
这你可错了，大错特错了
That isn't true, absolutely not true.
场景：洗澡和泥疗
1 27: showers and mud treatments.
场景：按摩
1 29: massages.
场景：走近
1 31 : inhalations.
你好，监督
Hello, Commendatore.
看，我明白了 你要说的是...
You know, I've figured out what you're trying to talk about...
是男人内心的挣扎 这要表现的更清晰些才行
Man's inner confusion. But you've got to be clearer.
你自己一定要十分清楚 要不就没有意义了
You have to make yourself understood. Otherwise what's the use of it?
我们走吧，贵都
Let's go, Guido.
除非你能说服我
If what you have to say is interesting,
要不然每个人都会象我这么想的
it must be so for everybody.
你怎么能不理观众的感受呢
How can you not care if audiences understand?
真对不起，这样太专横自大了
I'm sorry, but that is arrogant and presumptuous
监督，我们去哪边看看
Commendatore, let's go over there. Inhale. Breathe deeply.
你好，贵都
Hi, Guido.
我给你占了个好位置
I've saved you a spot by the jet.
我早上去看飞船模型了
I went to the spaceship this morning
已经有点模样了
and it's already gone up 50 meters...
马里奥
Mario.
贵都，再说一遍，我们都在恭候你
Guido, his Eminence is waiting for you. I repeat.
- 我们都在恭候你的光临
His Eminence is waiting.
快点穿上
Get dressed, quickly.
教主已经在等了
The Cardinal is already waiting.
全都告诉他吧
Tell him everything.
都认了吧，别再隐瞒了
Confess everything, don't hide anything
你要是还有时间，也跟我聊聊
and if you have any spare time just put in a good word for me too.
这可天赐良机，贵都 那可是教主啊，你太幸运了
It's a golden opportunity, Guido. The Cardinal! You're so lucky.
他能给我一切的...
He can give dispensations for anything...
记得我在墨西哥的婚姻么 帮我问问看
Remember my divorce in Mexico City. Get me my Mexican divorce.
他不会拒绝你的
He won't say no to you.
忏悔之前，记得跪下
And above all show you're devout, throw yourself down on your knees,
亲吻他的戒指，伤心的说，你要忏悔
kiss his ring, cry, say you've repented.
这样你以后就会心想事成的
Getting in their good graces means you can have anything you want in life.
听好了
Listen to me.
小心了，贵都，我们永远支持你
Careful, Guido. We're in your hands.
你要珍惜这5分钟啊
You only get five minutes.
你说的对，我并不开心
Your Eminence, I'm not happy.
为什么? 你不需要这样的
Why should you be? That isn't your job.
我们并不是生来就快乐的
Who told you we come into the world to be happy?
圣经上说，人非圣贤
Origen says in his homilies: Extra Ecclesiam nulla salus.
主可以帮助你们解脱
There's no salvation outside the church.
让主来帮你解脱
Extra Ecclesiam, nemo salvatur.
出了教堂你就会全部解脱
No one will meet salvation, outside the church.
主会宽恕你的罪过
Salus extra Ecclesiam, non est.
There's no salvation outside the church.
有人会去天堂
Civitas dei. He who isn't in the City of God,
有人会去地狱
belongs to the City of the Devil.
欢迎大家来参观这人类伟大的发明
Come see this great human phenomenon, the fakir Siva,
它打破了所有同类的记录
who has broken all previous records...
有欧洲的专家来精心打造的...
our experiment is controlled daily by European experts...
20,000...22...23,000... 后面的女士们
20,000... 22... 23,000... and the lady in the back?
25,000 很好，有人出到24,000了
25,000? Very well, the bid is 24,000.
还有没有人出30,000
Do I hear 30,000?
太好了35,000...40,000 加油啊，快要得到了....
Splendid. 35,000... 40,000. Going, going...
最后一次竞价! 50,000 50,000块成交!
One more offer? 50,000, the bid is 50,000...
你来多久了? 有5天了吧
- When did you get here? - Around five.
我去过酒店了，可你不在
We went to the hotel, but you weren't there.
你还好嘛? 好，很好
How are you? - Fine, fine.
你和谁来的?
Who did you come with?
罗瑟拉和恩瑞克，泰迪也来了
With Rossella and Enrico. Tilde's here too.
我的宝贝，你终于是来了 你知道么，看起来挺好
Good girl. You actually came. You look good, you know?
嗨，罗萨
Hey there, Rossa.
我们很久没跳舞了，一年?
It's been a year since we last danced together.
陆纱，亲爱的，你对我很珍贵
Luisa, darling. You're my treasure.
你能来我真高兴 永远都是
I'm so happy you came. It's always the same.
你一离开我就...
As soon you're away...
觉得孤单
You feel lonely.
真的嘛?亲亲我好么 来吧
Is it true? Did you miss me? - Yes.
有谁不喜欢女士们的陪伴啊
You weren't enjoying the company of all these lovely ladies?
你通知他们了...
So you've noticed them...
你走后我一直很难平静
No flings since you left?
可怜的贵都，大男子主义
Poor Guido. And your famous virility?
看你笑的多甜 你喜欢我笑嘛?
- You smell so good. - Do you like it?
这屋子里的人都为你黯然失色
You're so light.
你的作品怎样了? 有进展了么
And how's your project going? Better?
哦，还没什么突破性的进展
Well, I don't think I've had any major breakthroughs.
这次碰到什么麻烦了?
But what's it about? What are you up to this time?
哦，我不该说这些的
Oh, sorry.
我没猜错的话，恩力克也来了吧
Listen, am I mistaken or has Enrico fallen for you?
她很可爱啊，不是么
She's adorable, isn't she?
好!太精彩了!!
Bravo. Very good.
晚上好斯格诺拉 看到你太好了
Evening signora. So nice to have you here.
谢谢
Thanks.
麦斯，我们随时效劳 我们可以开始么?
Maestro, we're at your service. Should we get going?
我来了
I'm coming.
我亲爱的，晚上你就知道了
My dear lady, tonight you'll see
看看一个制作人的疯狂
the depths of insanity a producer can fall into.
坦白说，我不想跟他握手
Frankly, I'd rather not shake hands with this one.
她一碰你，就知道你想什么
The moment she touches you she knows what you're thinking.
这还能有谁?
Who else could it be?
她是你的精神向导啊!
Your guiding spirit.
我们有那么亲密么?
Haven't you reached that stage of intimacy yet?
我能介绍我的姐妹给你么 真可爱的妹妹
- May I introduce my sister? - Ah, the beautiful little sister!
大导演，你很有吸引力嘛
You see the kind of women your director attracts?
幸会幸会
Delighted to meet you, Commendatore.
我刚拍了一部核战争的片子
I just finished a screenplay about nuclear warfare.
只有你这样有胆识的制作人才能做到
Only a producer of your courage could get it made.
这位漂亮的女士也是你的妻子么?
Does the beautiful sorceress belong to your harem too?
事实上是监制的
Iet's say I'm a sort of overseer.
现在好多了，有人开始帮你了
So are you any better? Has your isolation helped?
你看上去确实好多了
You do look better. - Really?
嘿，开个玩笑.真的，好点没? 其实，还有点担心
No. Just kidding. Are you better? Actually, I was a little worried.
你能让陆纱来，对她很好
It was good of you to ask Luisa to come.
只有让她来，她才能开心
The very thought made her happy.
如果你不坚持，我到是没想过要来 我来也没什么用的
If you don't mind I'd rather not come. My presence is futile.
快上车吧 不了，我还是上克诺斯雅的车吧
- Suit yourself. -No, my friend. I insist. Get in Conocchia's car.
开车吧，和劳拉一起
Sweetie move it, go with Laura.
你的老婆呢? 不知道，我也在找她
- Where's your wife? - I don't know. She was just here.
罗瑟拉，跟我们走吧
Rossella, come with us.
我有个很特别的故事要告诉你
Yes, I want to tell you a strange story.
我的妹妹是个修女 很早就去世了
My sister was a nun. She died very young
有天晚上，她的雕像突然变了个表情
and one night her portrait suddenly changed its expression.
来，上车吧
Please, get in.
好像预示着某种危险
Changed as if it wanted to warn me about some danger...
我做前面吧
I'll sit in the front.
几天后，我的叔叔说...
So a couple days later my uncle says,
我们去市场吧，孩子们
Let's go to the market, kid.
我觉得这是某种先兆
He drove an lsotta Fraschini... I was recounting a premonition...
你觉得是么?
So what do you think?
听导演说话你得思维敏捷点才行
You have to be a little crazy to listen to this director.
少来了，胡扯什么
Bundle up. It's damp.
罗那多，你在那儿?
Renato, where are you?
这呢，监督
Here, Commendatore.
我们要准备好第20个
We've gotta be ready for the 20th.
跟我来，女士们 小心点，路不太平坦
Follow me, ladies. Careful. The ground is bumpy.
我们得进度有点落后了 不是得，我们已经到70公里了
It seems to me we're a bit behind. - No. We're already up to 70 meters.
你说，陆纱这是怎么了?
Listen, what's up with Luisa?
她突然变得怪怪得 好像很紧张，害怕什么
She's changed all of a sudden. She's turned so nervous and angry.
我想是因为看到你太激动了吧
I don't know. She was so happy to come see you.
你可能说了一些让她难过得事.
You might have said something that upset her.
不可能. 那么这又是什么?
- Never. - And what's this?
我对这个格外地着迷.
I find this extraordinarily fascinating.
这个模型很有层次感
This model will be superimposed on the structure,
有一触即发的感觉.
to create the illusion that the rocket is on the launch pad.
对嘛? 对的.
- Am I right? - Right.
这就是触发它的平台.
This is the rocket's launch pad.
是整部电影的精华
The most important moment in the movie.
不许拍照. 就一个，监督.
No photos. - Just one, Commendatore.
你丈夫现在在忙什么啊?写科幻小说?
What is your husband up to this time? Science fiction?
我怎么知道?你问他.
What do I know? Ask him.
Giancarlo给他写了个非常美妙的关于火星人的故事.
Giancarlo wrote him such a beautiful story about Martians.
这个游乐园是干什么用的?
What is this amusement park for?
你根本不了解这需要多少的工作量.
You have no idea what a job this was.
没有一家建筑公司愿意接下它
No construction company wanted to take it on.
它整个都要修筑在沙子上.
It rests entirely on sand.
它需要多少的混凝土多少?
How much concrete did it take?
非常多!400吨.
Tons! 400 tons.
监督，如果你不介意
Commendatore, if you don't mind,
我不想再爬楼梯了，我有点头晕.
I'll stop at the end of this first flight. I have vertigo.
八千万你可以至少可以买10座公寓.
For 80 million you could buy at least ten apartments.
有点华而不实，和他一样
It's a pompous shack, just like him.
你这女孩对你的导演姐夫一点也不客气啊
The little sister-in-law is not exactly tender with our director.
没准她看上导演了 啊?
Maybe she's in love with him. - With him?
我整天都在祈祷能有个这样的丈夫呢
I pray day and night that I'll be spared a husband like him.
怎么? 还得爬楼梯啊!
What now? More climbing?
我倒是很乐意背你上去
I'd be glad to carry you.
这建筑可是花费不菲啊
When I think he made me spend 80 million on this structure.
要是有个好的布景就锦上添花了
Wouldn't a well-crafted backdrop have been better?
布景?那一点也不新鲜
A backdrop! That's out of your grandfather's time.
克诺斯雅，就这也花费了几百万么?
Besides, are they your millions, Conocchia?
陆纱，冷不冷? 穿上我的衣服
Luisa, are you cold? Take my jacket.
没关系，我不冷
No, no. Thank you.
那好吧，反正我们也快回酒店了
Anyway, we're going back to the hotel.
那里不对么?
Is something wrong?
怎么郁郁不乐啊
You've gotten sad all of a sudden. Am I wrong?
我没有啊
No. I'm not sad at all.
首先开始的是地球的画面
The sequence starts with an image of planet Earth
然后看到是核爆发时候的蘑菇云
completely wiped out by a thermonuclear war...
贵都，见到你很高兴 真的
Guido seemed glad to see you, really.
...剩余的人类试图乘坐飞船逃跑
...and the spaceship, our new Noah's Ark, tries to escape, while the rest of humanity
到其他星球上避难
seeks refuge on another planet.
十万，越来越多的人开始聚集
More than 1 0,000 extras, even 1 5,000, a tragic crowd.
电影里真的有这么壮观的场面么?
We're really going to see all this in your movie?
有个领袖开始大声喊着 他想吸引大家的注意
The prophet is raising his voice. He's decided to scare everybody.
当然了，电影就要标新立异才能吸引观众
Why not? Don't tell me you also love movies where nothing happens?
我的电影更是要这样
In my movie I have all sorts of things happen.
我尽量注入更多的元素
I'm putting everything in. Even a tap-dancing sailor.
赛拉，过来这
Sailor, come here.
你也会说美国话了?
What did you learn in America?
不是，我不喝水 跳段舞看看，我给你安排点戏
No, I don't want water. Dance and I'll give you a part.
跳吧
Dance.
你这是怎么了?
What's up with you? What's going on?
罗斯卡，可别这么教训我了 让我一点心情都没了
Rossella, cut the big sister tone. It puts me off right away.
大导演先生，我打算给我演什么呢
Mr. Director, what part do I get?
陆纱怎么看我啊?她想干什么呢?
What does Luisa think about me? What does she want to do?
我演什么呢?您想好了么?
What's my part? My part?
别捣乱!
Go away!
你了解陆纱的.她话不多
You know Luisa. She doesn't say much.
我是她最好的朋友，她的话也不多
Not even to me, and I'm her best friend.
我真的不懂她
I really don't know. She's lost.
今天这样，明天那样，从来都没谱
One day she says one thing, another day, something else.
可是，她对你
Unfortunately, I think the only thing she'd like
却从来没改变过
is for you to be someone else.
为什么?
Why?
这也是人之常情么
It's the mistake everyone makes.
我看那傻小子是不是有点喜欢她啊
But that kind little fellow, is he in love with her?
你喜欢这样么，你的内心是这么想的么?
You'd like that, so your conscience won't gnaw at you anymore.
你个混蛋
You're such a scoundrel.
可怜的恩瑞克，他好奇怪 可不是我一个人这么说
Poor Enrico, he's so awkward. Everybody's noticed.
陪她走走，多顺着她点
He hangs around, listens to her, keeps her company.
他人很不错的
He's a great friend.
我想我的思路还是很清晰的
I thought my ideas were so clear.
我想做点真实的电影 不蒙骗观众
I wanted to make an honest film. No lies whatsoever.
我要说的就就是...
I thought I had something so simple to say.
对每个人都有意义的
Something useful to everybody.
能名垂千史的
A film that could help to bury forever
这样的才有价值
all those dead things we carry within ourselves.
事实上，这样才能让我充满激情
Instead, I'm the one without the courage to bury anything at all.
现在我好困惑 这开关是控制...
And now I'm utterly confused. This launch pad to deal with...
我为什么总是感觉不对
I wonder why things turned out this way.
是那里出错了呢
When did I go wrong?
我无话可说了...
I really have nothing to say...
其实我说还是老毛病
but I want to say it all the same.
你的意思是，为什么救援队伍不来么?
And your spirits, why don't they come to my rescue?
你总说他们有很多要对我说
You always said they had plenty of messages for me.
告诉他们少说多做
Let them get to work!
我提醒过你注意自己的态度
I've already told you, your attitude is wrong,
你对他们太严厉了
Your curiosity toward them is childish.
你总是要万无一失
You want too many guarantees.
好了，他们到底怎么说的? 总是有麻烦事
- Fine, but what do they say? - Always the same thing. Even now.
他们做的也很好的 对你的需要也了如指掌
They're very reasonable spirits. They know you very well.
哪有怎样?
So?
他们说你天马行空 你也该有点条理了
They say you're free, but you must learn to choose.
你时间不多了，抓紧点吧
You don't have much time. And you have to hurry.
贵都，你过来么? 到底来不来?
Guido, are you coming up? Yes or no?
请到320房间来
Room 320, please.
没人在啊
Nobody's in.
好的，谢谢
Fine, thanks.
你头痛了吧
Have you got a headache?
恩，吃了点阵痛片
No, it's a tranquilizer.
常吃这个?
Do you take them often?
有时候吧，失眠的时候吃
Sometimes, to help me sleep.
你就别担心我了
What's worrying you now?
恩?
What?
没什么，你要好好照顾自己
Nothing. If you could only see yourself.
笑什么呢?
Why are you laughing?
我可没想过背叛你，就算我看不惯你
I don't think I could ever betray you, if only because I couldn't bear
欺骗多么可笑啊
the ridiculous effort of having to hide and lie.
对你来说太容易了
But obviously it's easy for you.
听着，陆纱.我真高兴你能来
Listen Luisa. I am very happy you're here,
我已经精疲力尽了
but I am very tired and sleepy.
睡会儿吧，晚安
Sleep then. Good night.
我不知道你怎么看我的
I don't know what you think my life is like, reducing it all
变成别人希望的那样
to the pettiness of somebody stealing from the cookie jar.
你了解我什么呢?我的喜好你知道么
What do you know about my life? What I hate and what I don't.
我只了解我看到的
I only know what you show me.
那我是什么样的?
What am I showing you?
说吧，你觉得我是什么样的人
Come on, tell me what you see.
说说你的道德标准
You and your judgmental moralism. What are you getting at?
没什么，我们好久没有倾心的聊聊了
Nothing. I know we've been stagnating for years.
这都是因为你；你总是不让我说
But it's you; you're the one who always calls me back
所以我们才没机会
and wants to start all over again.
我只求你这一次，不要再重新开始了
Once and for all, I don't want to restart anything.
那该怎样?
But what do you want?
你要我来一定有原因吧 说说看
Why did you want me here? What good am I to you?
为什么要我来，我能帮你点什么呢?
What are you trying to get from me? What is it you want?
别烦，我昨晚已经去的时候已经找到她了
Don't fret. I'd already spotted her last night when I got in.
我没问，她也没提起
I've asked no questions, so don't say a word.
你就是要我听你撒谎来的么?
Spare me the embarrassment of having to listen to your lies.
她长的真可爱
She must have been born in March or April.
她一定是个白羊座的，典型的
She's got all the characteristics of an Aries. She's the Aries type.
还是我来告诉你吧
I'll tell you what type she is.
将来绝对是个可塑之材
Exactly the type most likely to make
一个没有个性和主见的人
a good companion for feeble, spineless, confused men.
陆纱，我不明白
Luisa, I didn't know.
我和你一样，也是第一次见到她
I'm seeing her for the first time, like you.
真的，就像这里一样，很多人
Really, in a place like this, where there are so many people,
她处境也不好，不用很奇怪
it's no surprise to run into the poor thing.
难怪你从昨晚开始就折磨我
So this is why you've been tormenting me since last night.
你也应该说清楚嘛
You should have told me.
最让我接受不了的是
What annoys me most is that people could think
人们认为我只接触有品味的人
I'd go with somebody who dresses that way.
你怎么知道她的品味的?
Have you seen her clothes?
我们走走好吗
Listen, can't we go for a walk?
还是换个话题吧
Let's not talk about this anymore.
这三年来你总是这样 好了，够了!
It's been over for three years. Finished. Enough.
你快让我疯了 他装正经的
He drives me crazy. He pretends he's telling the truth.
他的诚实都是虚伪的 觉得自己总是对的
He acts honest. As if he's the one who's right.
你怎么能接受这些呢?
How can you live this way?
这么活着多累啊
It's not right living this way,
对谁都没有句真心话
not letting others know what's true and what's false.
你能不能改变一下呢? 你到底能不能改改啊?
Is it possible that for you it's all the same? How?
你说的对，我是很乏味
You're right. I know, I'm boring.
这样的生活难道你不痛苦么
How sad having to play the bourgeois wife who doesn't understand.
那你说，我该怎样好?
You tell me, what should I do.
我其实不该取笑你的
I really can't laugh about it the way you do.
亲爱的，我不是取笑你的
No darling, I'm not laughing.
你跟她说了什么啊?
What do you tell her?
最让我难以忍受的是，你把她带进我们的生活
What disgusts me the most is that you've mixed her up in our life.
她知道我和你的一切
She knows everything about you and me.
这婊子，真可恶!
That whore. Cow!
你的痛苦你自己清楚
You're a real pain, you know.
还有...
And yet...
斯格诺拉 卡尔拉，你唱歌真的很动听
Signora Carla, you sing so well.
那只是业余爱好罢了
No, I'm just an amateur.
你看上去还是那么迷人
And how pretty you look.
我一直都想一睹尊容 真的
I've wanted to meet you for so long. - And l, you.
你可真够时髦的了
You're so stylish.
不，你才是真正时髦的呢 我?事实上，很随便的
No, you're the stylish one. Me, frankly, I'm a bit trashy.
开什么玩笑，这再普通不过了
What are you talking about? This is so refined.
你也喜欢嘛?
Do you like it?
这是我在一个时装展览上找到的 是吗!
It's a little outfit I found in Vogue. - Really?
你要知道我可花费了不少心思
If you only knew how long it took me to find it.
可你不知道，如果卡尔拉要是喜欢她就会...
But you know, when Carla wants something...
他到了!
Here he comes!
贵都来了
Guido's here.
晚上好，女士
Good evening, women.
快关上门，外面有暴风!
Close the door, there's a storm.
你还好吗?感觉怎么样?
How are you? Well?
礼物上都有你们的名字
Every gift comes with its nametag.
别弄混了，这是卡塔锐娜的
Don't get mixed up. This is Caterina's.
他太可爱了
He's a darling!
这个是姐夫给你的
And this one is for my darling sister-in-law,
因为她越来越善解人意了
because she's finally understood how things should be.
我们这就给你放水洗澡
We'll draw your bath right away.
格劳瑞，这就是你想要的
Gloria, this is you-know-what.
谢谢.贵度，待会儿我想跟你谈谈
Thanks. I need to talk to you, Guido.
我知道她想说什么
I know what she wants to tell you.
我们得把她支开了 因为她已经开始吃醋了
Now we'll have to send her away because she's acting jealous.
我们在楼上说什么来着?
What were you doing upstairs?
我猜到她想说什么了 这个角色非我莫属了
I went to see those poor things. They'd always be alone, if not for me.
对她不合适，她根本就不适合演这个角色
The role doesn't suit her. She's only a common bourgeoise.
她一点见地也没有
She has no class.
让他安静会儿，他该洗澡去了
Leave him alone now. He's got to take his bath.
哦，贵都，我就是喜欢这种款式的 我做梦都想要一个呢
Oh Guido, this is splendid, I've always wanted one like it.
快点，卡尔拉，寒迪!拿着桶
Hurry, Carla, Hedy! Get the buckets.
贵都，我丈夫来信了
Guido, my husband wrote.
他让我回去过新年 一天就行，你不会介意吧?
He wants me home for New Year's, just for a day, do you mind?
除非你自己不想做 回去吧，没关系的
If you do, I'll tell him I can't. - I think that will be fine.
快来，卡咯塔
Come on, Carlotta!
看看这位小姐 给你来点惊喜
- Who's that little black girl? - A surprise from us.
她是夏威夷来的，你不记得拉
She's from Hawaii, don't you remember her?
你不是跟我们提过好多次了么
You told us about her so many times.
谢谢你，陆纱，你对我太好了
Thank you, Luisa. You're so kind.
这礼物好精致!我太喜欢了
Such a delicate little present.
那个发卡是我的啊
That tiara is mine.
哦，知道 我看看就给你
Yes, I know. I'll give it back to you later.
哦，亲爱的
Oh, darling!
看到你好高兴
What a thrill to find you here.
你好吗! 好
- How are you? - Fine.
还没告诉我你是谁呢
But do tell me, who are you?
名字并不重要，我只是相见见你
The name doesn't matter. I'm happy to be here.
可别再问我问题了，我留下好吗?
Don't ask me any questions. - Can I stay?
当然了，你这么可爱，留下吧 我现在有点忙.
Of course, you pretty thing. I'm busy now.
待会儿再聊吧
But later?
罗瑟拉? 你在这干吗啊?
Rossella? What are you doing here?
当然是来当女主角的啊 你同意嘛?
Playing Pinocchio's wise cricket. Do you mind?
是什么让你这么开心啊?
No. But why are you laughing?
没什么啊.我只是想看看你在这如何风流
It's nothing. I just want to see how you get out of this one.
你总是生活在花丛中 我的王子
You've finally got your harem, King Solomon!
那都是过去的事了 一直都是吧
- It was high time. - Sure was.
等我下来
Lower me down.
你胆子好大哦
Aren't you a little scared?
有什么可怕的啊?
Of what? Everything is going great.
我也能留下嘛?我玩的好开心哦
Can I stay too? I'm having such fun.
我不会添麻烦的，只要看着你就足够了
I don't want anything. I'll just watch you.
我们有规定，这样是不行的
We have rules that must be respected. Do you know that?
过来，帮我拉一下
Come, help me.
这可是份贵重的礼物哦
It's a two piece suit with a busby in ostrich feathers. Do you like it?
嗨，亨迪，你好漂亮
Hi Hedy, it's beautiful.
有什么规矩呢?
So, what are the rules?
还不清楚，不过导演答应个角色，而且还有
I don't know. He promised me a part in his movie and said
我要不停的换漂亮衣服
I'd have to change dresses a lot.
行了，姑娘们，快让我出来吧
Girls, that's enough. Get me out.
格劳瑞，爽身粉给我 好的，来了
- Gloria, the talcum powder. - Ah, yes.
贵都，你知道嘛，她给你准备了你最喜欢的
Guido, do you know she prepared something just the way you like it?
那是什么? 蛋糕啊
- Really? - A cake.
你快乐嘛，我的姑娘
- Are you happy, girls? - Of course!
这不就是你一直说要的嘛
Isn't this just what you always wanted?
就是这个了!世界上最美的孩子
Certainly! Isn't he the best kid in the world?
纳迪，快拿爽身粉过来
Nadine, hurry up with the powder!
哦，纳迪，这就是你在哥本哈根说得
Oh Nadine, what was it you used to say in Copenhagen?
欢迎我们的客人
We're delighted to invite our passengers
和我们一起度过这美好的哥本哈根夜晚
to spend the night in Copenhagen due to a problem with the motor.
多么美好的声音啊
Just listen to her voice...
制作组会买单的
The company will cover all expenses.
大家好好睡吧
Good night to you all.
马德林，帮我一下
Madeleine, come help us.
撒拉都 在这呢，我来照顾贵都好了
- Saraghina! - Here I am. I'll carry Guido.
可怜的人，水很烫吧，他都烫红了
Oh, my poor man. The water was scalding. He's turned all red!
噢，好健壮的腿啊 真是太吸引人了
- Such nice, thin legs. - Straight like when he was a boy.
他总是表现的那么天真 可是内心却很丰富
He likes to act like a kid, but he's really very complex.
别傻了.我太了解他了 一个伪君子罢了
Don't be fooled. I'm onto him. He's a hypocrite.
不是这样的
No, he's not.
可他从来不跟我们讲真话
But why does he have to tell everything to anybody?
他知道怎么处理这些事的
He knows how to stand up for himself.
贵都，你也不帮帮我
Guido, help me.
这是谁在喊叫?
Who's screaming like that?
杰奎琳，她不愿意上楼去陪那个老头
Jacqueline. She refuses to go upstairs with the old ones,
我们把她关进地窖里去了
so we've locked her in the cellar.
简直是侮蔑!我可不原和这些婆娘说话
It's scandalous. I don't want to have to speak to those witches,
他太老了，而我才26啊
so much older than me. I'm 26. Go to the Paris public register.
杰奎琳，今年才26， 生于1938年7月1日
Jacqueline Bon Bon, 26, the 4th of July 1 938.
你凭什么让我走?
You have no right to send me upstairs.
还没年轻着呢 看看我，浑身都是青春的活力
It's not my time yet. Look, I'm so agile. Look at my legs.
你们谁的腿象我的一样有弹性?
Which one of you has such a tight little ass? Look at my chest.
贵都，不要让我上楼嘛 我不要上去
Guido, don't send me upstairs. I don't want to go upstairs.
规矩就是规矩，上去吧
You know the rules. The rules are the rules.
贵都, 我....
Guido l...
安静点，其实楼上不是很好么
Calm down. Apparently it's nice upstairs, too.
给你个耳环好了 这还差不多
- Your earring. Here. - Thank you.
你一直这么爱我的，就让我多呆会儿吧
You've always loved me. Please, tell him to give me an extension.
贵都，我们就给她个例外吧
Guido, couldn't we give her an extension?
小心点，你压到我了
What are you doing? You're breaking my balls too?
求求你了，一年就这一次么
I beg you Guido, just for one year.
不行 我是不会上楼去的
- No extension. - I'm not going upstairs.
你说什么? 我不要上楼去!
- What did you say? - I'm not going upstairs.
你敢再说一遍!
- Say it again if you dare. - I'm not going upstairs!
她疯了，我就早说不该让她来的
This one is crazy. I told you we should never have let her in.
你，看看你的合约
Hey, girl! Just look at your rulebook.
凡是到了年龄的，必须要上楼去的
Whoever passes the age limit shall be removed to the upper floors,
你也能不例外!
where she shall be treated equally well,
凭什么她就可以搞特殊
but shall live basking in her memories.
这很荒诞，我们为什么要接受呢
It's so disgusting, absurd, we shouldn't have accepted it.
不可能，必须遵守
Never, right from the start.
这本来就不公平!
It's not fair!
规矩定了就必须遵守
These are rules invented by someone
没有遵守规矩的人
who doesn't pass the test himself.
根本就是个耻辱
In France such a man would be the shame of the nation.
榨完了油水就想甩了，是么
Are we lemons to thrown out after we're squeezed?
贵都，她们说得没错 你就是个禽兽
- Guido, they're so right. - You're a monster.
是时候了
Our time has come!
杰奎琳是对的，我们要争取自由
Hurray for Jacqueline, who has shown us the way to our freedom.
打倒这个负心的男人!
Down with the tyrant, down with Bluebeard!
我们有被爱的权利，哪怕我们老了也有!
We have the right to be loved 'til we're 70 years old.
打倒他!
Down with him!
你以为你是谁? 你很年轻么?
And what do you think you are? A boy?
让我们再说一遍，他跟本不会享受性爱
Let's say it once and for all, he doesn't know how to make love.
根本就不会
That's the truth.
不懂得怜香惜玉，不理会我们感受的人
- And he falls asleep right away. - I don't sleep. I think.
贵都，我们老了就都不要了，是么
Guido, don't send us upstairs when we get old.
打倒他!打倒他!
Down, down.
来吧，让我们推翻他吧
Quick! They're rebelling upstairs too.
哦，太好了
Oh, delicious!
你这个狼心狗肺得，骗子!我从巴黎特地 赶来，我的戏呢?
You pig, you liar. I came all the way from Paris. What's my part?
贵都，没人再给你演了 这样你开心了吧
Guido, who will dance for you? You liked it so much.
我现在不喜欢这样了
I don't like it anymore.
陆纱，别走，帮帮我
Luisa, help me!
对不起，我不该干涉你的事
Sorry, but I don't meddle in my husband's business.
如果他觉得这么做好，我就会支持他 这是早就定好了的
If this is his decision, it's good. Those are the rules.
快点，贵都，洗澡水凉了
Hurry up Guido, the soup's getting cold.
看不到我正焦头烂额么
Can't you see I'm busy?
他可真是与众不同啊
What an extraordinary man.
是啊，却...
Yes, but...
他已经习惯这样了，每晚都是
He needs to act this way. He does it almost every night.
贵都，你还记得我么?
Guido, do you remember me?
亲爱的，让你受惊吓了 我会给你温暖的
But darling, you're wounded; I'll get you some cream...
我只想要你的安慰
- I don't want any cream. - Some balm.
我只想你安慰安慰我
- I don't want any balm. - Drops...
他是不会抛弃你的
It's not true that he dumps you like squeezed lemons.
他会一直留你在身边的
Actually, he'd like to keep you all with him always.
他真的很有风度
He is too good, too patient.
我，不会留下我的
No, not me, no.
他不喜欢你了，你已经不年轻了
He doesn't like you. You're old.
亲爱的杰奎琳，我们只想要一个机会就够了
Dear Jacqueline, we're happy to have had the opportunity
只要和你在一起，能在楼上也很满足了
to live with you and we wish you the best of luck upstairs.
我们代表贵都向你保证
We'd like to reassure you on Guido's behalf
你会第一个在他的片子里出演的
that you were the first showgirl in his life.
你现在就可以尽情唱歌跳舞了
You're now entitled to a song and dance of your choice,
就在这聚光灯下
with your very own spotlight.
姑娘们，谢谢你们，你们对我太好了
Thank you girls, you're so kind.
我来唱支情歌吧
Would you like me to sing a love song?
来点性感的 好啊，性感的我最在行了
No, better something sexy. That was my specialty.
贵都，记得意大利最大的阿波罗电影院么
Guido, remember the Apollo theater in Bologna?
当然了
Yes, I do.
还是来首欢快的歌曲吧
No, better a happy song!
哦，我的项链掉了
Oh, I've lost my pearls.
哦，再来一次
Oh, again!
你听都不听
You're not even listening.
再见了，贵都
Farewell, Guido.
这太好笑了
I thought it was such a funny situation,
整部片子的精华都在这了
the funniest part of my story.
我有点话想跟大家说
I'd even prepared a little speech to give at the table:
亲爱的，快乐永远属于最真实的人们
Darlings, happiness is being able to tell the truth
真诚会带给大家幸福
without ever making anybody suffer.
下面卡尔拉准备弹提琴给我们听
Carla would have played the harp, as on any night,
相信你们会喜欢的
and we would have been happy hiding in here,
在那遥远的地方.献给所有人
far away from the world. All of you and l.
你怎么了，为什么悲伤?
What's wrong? Why this sadness?
看，他也觉得空虚了
See? We've made him feel guilty.
不是这样吧，贵都
That's not it, Guido.
这个夜晚太美好了
It has been a wonderful evening.
你怎么可以伤心呢
You mustn't be sad.
你来点什么喝的?
Do you need anything?
她们待会儿都会睡了 我还要收拾一下
Now they'll all go to bed and I still have a lot to do:
洗衣服，刷碗，还要擦地板
the laundry, all the dishes, mend the sheets, scrub the floors
然后还要准备明天的早餐
and set up breakfast for tomorrow.
我们大家住在一起不是很好么
Aren't we fine living all together this way?
起先我也不太理解
At first I didn't understand,
可事实都已经这样了
that this is the way things are meant to be.
现在已经...
But now...
你看我不是很好么? 我不会给你添麻烦了
Don't you think I'm good now? I don't bother you anymore.
我不会再问你问题了
I don't ask questions.
有点晚了 20年了，我才明白
A bit slow, wasn't l? It's taken me 20 years to understand.
我都结婚20年了，才有今天
20 years since the day we got married
你是我的丈夫，我是你的妻子
and you became my husband and I your wife.
你还记得么，记得我们结婚那天么
Do you remember Guido? Do you remember that day?
如果你再多一点耐心
If you could only be patient a little longer, Luisa.
你可能早就明白了
But perhaps you've had it.
事实上，我真的想听听更多的意见
Frankly, I'd love to be able to offer a word of advice.
可是今晚，你全部都解决了
But I think tonight you're called
事实上根本就没有答案
to solve a problem for which there is no solution.
给每个人都找到一个位置
Finding a precise face for a crowd of characters
有的人生是那么肤浅，平淡，乏味!
that in your script are so rough, so vague, so superficial...
我们看的是什么片子?
What is it we're watching?
我不知道，只是个片断吧
I don't know... screen tests.
你觉得不好么
You're not well.
完全相反，我觉得还不错
Quite the contrary.
阿哥斯蒂娜，走段猫步再加上点舞蹈
Agostini, get on the catwalk and do a little dance for us.
我用钢琴给你伴奏
I'll accompany you on the piano.
听这段， “孤独的岁月
Listen here. "The solitary ego
一直在重复，从不间断，
that revolves around itself and feeds upon itself, ends up
结局总是哭泣，或者狂笑”
strangled by a great cry or a great laugh."
这段是他在意大利流浪的时候写的
Words that Stendhal wrote during his stay in ltaly.
如果我们再多一点点幻想
If we sometimes read those sayings on chocolate wrappers
而不是盲目的听，就能体会里面的意境
instead of throwing them away, we would be spared many an illusion.
终于找到他了. 原来在门旁边准备逃跑呢
There he is. By the door, always ready to run away.
大家晚上好，让你们就等了
Good evening to you all and apologies for the delay.
现在要来点什么呢?
Well, what are you up to now?
贵都在那? 我在这呢!
- Guido where are you? - Here.
下来! 还是让我在这吧
- Come down. - I'd rather stay up here.
晚上好，原来你也在 我们开始吧
Evening... Good, you're here too. Let's get going.
马上开始
Right away.
他们取消了今晚所有的活动让我们用场地
They skipped the variety act tonight so we could use the theater.
好，开始
Let's go.
年轻人，是时候觉醒了
Young man, it's time to make up your mind.
我把所有的剪辑带过来了
I've brought all the screen tests...
你说什么克诺斯雅，刚才你说什么?
Pardon me Conocchia, but the time for his jokes is over.
他的所有猜疑，都是幻想而已
All his doubts, his uncertainties, his whims.
他已经有足够时间准备 我们今晚就来作出选择吧
He had all the time he wanted, but tonight we're here to choose.
这就是为什么我们来这 是啊
- That's why we're all here. - Right.
克诺斯诺已经得到他想要的一切
Conocchia has gotten everything from Rome.
前后所有的剪接片断，甚至5个月前拍的都给他了
The new and the old screen tests, even the ones we shot five months ago.
就让我们一个个的看 然后说：
Now we'll go through them one by one, and you have to say:
那个是妻子，那个是情人
This is the wife, this is the mistress,
那个是教主，你们清楚了嘛?
this is the Cardinal, this is Saraghina. Clear?
我可不想让整个意大利电影界笑话
I don't want to be the joke of the ltalian film industry
最主要的我不想让你们失望
but above all I don't want you to end up that way.
他们都开始抨击你了
They're all ready to shoot you down.
你还有几个朋友在支持你，一个都没有
You've got very few friends left, on the Left or the Right.
只有我在一直日日夜夜的帮助你
But I am here to help you each and every way.
我们必须，而且马上重新开拍
We must start shooting and we must do it immediately.
放片子吧
Roll the screen tests.
奥林帕小姐的片断
Miss Olimpia's screen test.
奥林帕小姐的...
Miss Olimpia...
要关门么? 好的，关上吧
- Should I shut the door? - Yes. Sway, sway your big hips.
把东西放下
Put down your stuff. Good.
现在到镜子那去，欣赏一下自己
Now go to the mirror. Admire yourself.
继续，挺起你的胸 就是这样
More. Swell your chest. There.
走到电话那 慢一点，不要太快
Now go to the phone. Slowly. Don't run.
你不要跑! 我没跑啊
- Why are you running? - I'm not.
好，走到这，到地板上的标记这
Look, hit that mark. There, on the floor.
你好，我找下门卫
Hello, the concierge please?
这就是
Speaking.
给我送杯水来
I'd like a bottle of flat water.
开水么?
Fiuggi.
不，开水太热
No, Fiuggi is sparkling.
往这里看! 水没有那么热
No, look this way. Fiuggi is the least sparkling.
那好吧
Fine, I'll take the Fiuggi.
这个怎样?贵都
Will this one do, Guido?
她能不能改变主意， 不要离别英格兰
He's got to make up his mind because she's leaving for England.
她下周才走呢，贵都
She's leaving next week, Guido.
这位是谁啊? 你别插嘴!
- And who's this one? - Shut up, you!
你喜欢这个演员么?
Or do you prefer this one.
这可是个重要的角色
This is an important character.
观众的第一印象就应该非常好 对吧，贵都
People need to like her right off the bat. Right, Guido?
斯格诺拉，累了就坐下吧
Signora, sit down as if you were drained.
这个女性角色，失去了挑战生活的勇气
This character is a woman who has lost the desire to fight.
因为...说你的台词
because... say your line...
一直不停么? 什么?
- Without stopping? - What?
真的不停么? 对，是的
- Without stopping? - Yes, yes.
你可以完全自由发挥
I am the one who's offering you complete freedom.
总之，这样对你不好的 我其实并不惹人喜欢
Anyway, I'm no good to you this way. I'm just a nuisance.
这位是谁? 她代表谁呢?
And who's this? What should she represent?
你听不到么? 她是你的老婆
Didn't you hear? She's the wife.
别停，她很可爱，充满热情 你是这么认为么?
Still, she's likable, soulful. Don't you think?
给我支烟 我也没有了，恩力克帮我们买盒烟去
- Gimme a cigarette. - I've run out. Enrico, fill us up.
我这有 哦，谢谢
- Here you go. - Thank you.
别客气
You're welcome.
我不能这样活下去了
I cannot go on like this any longer.
现在，你告诉我，我该是什么样的
Now, you tell me how I should be.
做一个永远不对别人撒谎，欺骗的人
Not someone who lies and swears he's telling the truth
哪怕一会儿
every second of the day.
这样的要求你做的到么? 你从来都做不到
That would be enough. You don't even do that.
和你在一起，我从来都没有知道过真相
With you I never, never know the truth.
一点点的小事你也欺骗
Even in the smallest things.
陆纱，那是因为我考虑你的感受
Luisa, I care for you.
撒谎对你太平常了
Lying is like breathing to you.
请再说一次
Repeat that, please.
撒谎对你太平常了
Lying is like breathing to you.
你是个厚颜无耻的人
So brazen.
他的生活一直都是这样 没错
- All lines from his life. - Right.
我认识她，还是个公主呢
I know this one. She's the princess.
我不是已经一个人了么? 你还能给我什么呢?
Am I not alone already? What are you giving me?
我还能企盼什么呢?
What have I got to look forward to?
看这边，然后戴上眼镜
Look this way. Put on the glasses.
重复最后一句的台词
Repeat the last line.
我难道不是一个人么?
Am I not alone already?
你一定要说么 对，一定要说
You have to say it, yes, aggressively,
再掺杂点感情
but also with deep bitterness.
他说：什么? 你要分开?
He said:. What? You want a separation.
你要一个人么?
You want to be alone.
你一个人怎么生活啊?
But what would you do on your own?
她回答说：为什么不? 我不是已经一个人了么?  照着说
And she answers:. why, am I not alone already? Go on.
贵都，从来都不要怀疑，她是个完美的女人
Guido, there's no doubt about this one. She's perfect.
5个月.我们都分开5个月了
Five months. We've been going this way for five months.
可是她们都老了啊
But they're all so old!
水好了
Fiuggi is sparkling.
不，这水一点也不热 “大声点说”
No, it's the least sparkling. Louder.
好，放下电话
Put down the phone.
奥莉帕的片断
Screen test for Miss Olimpia.
这个怎样?
What about this one?
离开我你会很危险的
It's dangerous leaving me alone.
为什么，你干什么了?
Why, what do you do?
我要再说一次么?
Should I repeat the line?
不用了，把你的头转过来一点点 好，停!
No, just turn your little head this way. Now, stop.
你要去哪里?
Where are you going?
当然是回酒店，我好困了!
Back to the hotel. I'm sleepy.
等等，听我说
Wait a second. Listen.
发生什么事了么?
What happened?
没什么，我们之间也发生不了什么了
Nothing. Nothing ever happens between us.
你看到什么不开心的事了么?
Were you offended by something you saw?
只是拍电影而已
It's just a movie.
我是第一个醒悟的
I'm the first to understand that.
电影，只是个新的发明罢了，骗人的机器
It's a movie, another invention, another lie.
你把所有的感情放进去，都变成你希望的那样
You put everybody in it, but the way you like to see them.
可我知道真相!
But I know the truth.
不同的是我不会去
The difference is that I would never have the impudence
告诉别人你的厚颜无耻了!
to tell everybody the way you do.
去拍你的电影吧!
Go ahead. Make your movie.
不，我不会
No, I won't.
再放纵我自己，任你们的自私滋长
Indulge yourself. Stroke your ego.
你能告诉大家你很伟大
Go make everyone think you're so wonderful.
可是你不能告诉人们
What could you ever teach strangers when you can't
你最真实的一面
even tell the simplest truth to the ones closest to you?
我们永远看到的你真实的那一面
To the one who's been growing old with you?
好了陆纱，别说这些了
Come on Luisa. Cut the drama.
你叫我来是对的
You were right to ask me here.
我们该结束了
We needed to find closure.
这次，我保证不会再回心转意了
This time, I assure you, I won't be coming back.
你可以去死了
You can go to hell!
好吧，走吧，走吧!
Fine, just run, run.
你快走吧
Do what the doctor ordered, run!
闭嘴!把这个无知的人赶走!
Shut up! Throw this ignoramus out.
好了，你快唱吧
Fine, now sing.
你可能以为我弄错了 可是帐单还在没结...
You may say I'm losing it, but I have the bills here...
让我付这个，做梦! 克诺斯雅，你做梦去吧
I'll never pay this one, never! Conocchia, you're losing it.
萨拉娜看，我们有钱了
Saraghina look, we've got the money.
萨拉娜，跳舞吧，跳伦巴吧!
Saraghina, the Rumba, the Rumba...
贵都，说点什么吧，求求你了
Guido, would you please say something? Please!
这个合格么，贵都?
What about this one, Guido?
我还是喜欢前面那个
Frankly I preferred the one before.
这人是南方来的
This one is from Naples.
你看不出来我...很烦么?
Can't you see that I'm... stuttering.
你什么时候开始，我已经等烦了
When are you coming? I'm tired of waiting.
看着我的眼睛
Look at me.
不要离开我，我好怕
Don't leave me alone! You know it's dangerous.
不要离开我，我需要依靠，亲爱的
Don't leave me alone. You know it's dangerous, darling.
看这边!
Look over here.
你怎么还不来? 不要让我再等待了
Why aren't you coming now? Why are you keeping me waiting?
你知道让我在这等是不安全的
You know it's dangerous when I have to wait.
大声，再大声点儿，行不行啊
Louder, louder!
伯爵夫人，继续走
Countess, walk.
不要碰我
Don't touch me.
这边来，到这边
This way, this way.
格瑞斯小姐，片断一
Screen tests Mrs. Grazia, one.
露出你的肩来，要快!
Just bare your shoulders all of a sudden.
萨拉娜，我们有钱了，有钱了!
Saraghina, we've got the money. The money.
停，非常好.可以通过么?
Stop. Very good. Was it all right?
斯诺格拉，你看可以么?
Signora, what do you think?
如果都不表态，我们看还有什么意义
If he won't speak up, at least we can say something.
都说说意见，我们很民主的嘛，对不对?
Somebody say something! This is a democracy, right?
你不要躲了，呵呵，还好嘛?
You can't hide. We've found you anyway. How are you?
我是勃利迪，是珂劳迪亚的经纪人
Hi, I'm Poletti, from Claudia's press agency.
15年前见过的，不过您可能不记得了
We met 1 5 years ago. You might not remember me...
看，她过来了 那呢?
- Look, she's here. - Where?
失陪一下
Excuse me.
珂劳迪亚，你好吗?
- Claudia. - How are you?
还不错，谢谢 你终于来了
Well, and you? You're finally here.
我们出去聊聊，可以吗?
Let's go outside, all right?
这是卡罗琳，我的女秘书
This is Caroline, my secretary.
我想和你单独谈谈
I'd like to talk to you alone.
我们什么时候开拍?
When do we start shooting?
快了，马上 我的那部份剧本呢
- Soon, very soon. - And what's my part?
我等会儿会告诉你的
I'll tell you everything later.
真高兴能和你合作
I'm very happy to be working with you
我希望能帮上你的忙
and I hope I'll be able to help you.
快跟我讲讲
But you must tell me everything.
我们这是去哪?
Where are we going now?
哦，是这边
Well? - This way.
你真的太漂亮了 任何语言在你面前都显得苍白
You're so beautiful. I'm at a loss for words.
你让我心跳不已，像个孩子一样
You make my heart beat like a school boy's.
你不信我吗，嗯?
You don't believe me, do you?
是你让我重新燃起对生命的激情
You inspire such deep respect.
你爱的是谁? 珂劳迪亚，你喜欢我么?
Who do you love? Claudia, who are you with?
我最关心的是谁? 当然是你啊
- Who do you care for? - You.
知道么，你来的太是时候了
You arrived just in time, you know.
你在坏笑什么?
Why do you smile that way?
我连想都不敢想你会这么看我 不要嘲讽我了
I never know if you're judging me, absolving me, mocking me.
我想听听你的意见，告诉我 你怎么看这部电影
I'm listening. You said you wanted to tell me about the film.
其实我不懂什么
I don't know anything.
你能不能先把别的事放一放 然后我们从头来说
Could you leave everything behind and start from zero again?
一件一件事聊 我们好好探讨一下
Pick one thing, and one only, and be absolutely devoted to it?
我们生存的意义
Make it the reason for your existence,
是因为世间的人和事是互相关联的
the thing that contains everything, that becomes everything,
只要我们认真去做好每一件事，就会成功的 你能做到么?
because your dedication to it makes it last forever? Could you?
好，听着，如果我问你，珂劳迪亚...
All right, listen. If I were to say, Claudia...
今后你打算怎么办? 我不知道该怎么办...
Where are we going? I don't know the way...
你会怎么说?
And what about you? Could you?
春天已经不远了 看着我，转过来
The springs must be nearby. Listen. Turn here.
你眼前的我，决不会
No, this guy here, he couldn't.
放弃任何人和事，他要抓住一切机会
He wants to grab everything, can't give up a single thing.
他每天都在进步
He changes his mind every day,
因为他不想和成功擦肩而过
because he's afraid he might miss the right path.
他会这样一直追求到底 这就是这部电影的结局么?
And he's slowly bleeding to death. - So this is how the movie ends?
不，这是电影的开始
No, this is how it starts.
他会碰到一个如春天一样美丽的姑娘
Then one day he meets the girl of the spring.
她会给人们带来希望
She's one of those girls that distributes the healing water,
她是一个美丽，善良，淳朴的女人
she's beautiful, young and ancient, a child and a woman already,
真实而又饱满 她绝对可以拯救心灵
authentic and radiant. There's no doubt that she's his salvation.
你又着披肩长发，穿着洁白的裙子
You'll be dressed in white and your hair will be long,
就象你现在穿的一样
just the way you wear it.
把灯关了吧
Turn the headlights off.
然后呢?
And then?
我们离开这里
Let's leave.
可我不喜欢这，不够真实
I don't like this place. It doesn't feel real.
我喜欢大的场景，这有点奇怪么?
I like it enormously. Isn't that odd?
我还不能体会你的意境
I didn't get much from your story.
这个角色很像你自己 一个不会真正去爱的人
A guy like your character, who doesn't love anybody,
是不会轻易坠入爱河的
is not very sympathetic you know.
这是他的错，他还能想得到什么?
It's his fault. What does he expect?
你以为我真的不懂么?
You think I don't know that?
你真的是顽固不化
You're a bit of a bore too.
难道一点批评都不能接受?
You really can't take the least bit of criticism.
你戴那顶帽子太好玩了，像个老头子一样
You're so funny with that big hat, made up like an old man.
我不明白.他需要一个女人带给他全新的生活
I don't understand. He meets a girl that can give him a new life
又把她推走?
and he pushes her away?
是因为他不再相信...
Because he no longer believes in it.
他自己会真的去爱一个人
Because he doesn't know how to love.
他相信没有任何女人可以改变他
Because it isn't true that a woman can change a man.
事实上他根本不懂得爱
Because he doesn't know how to love.
总之我觉得这次很真实
And above all because I don't feel like telling another pile of lies.
因为他真的不懂得爱
Because he doesn't know how to love.
我真的抱歉 让你这么远道而来
I'm sorry, Claudia, for making you come all the way here.
别再虚伪了
You're such a fake.
电影里面根本就没有我的角色
So, there's no part in the film.
是啊，找不到这样的角色
You're right. There isn't.
事实上也没有电影 什么都没有
And there's no film. There's nothing anywhere.
如果我可以拿主意 我会把所有人遣散了
If it were up to me we would call it all off now.
哦，原来你在这呢
Ah, here you are.
下周就开拍了，你去了那了?
Where did you go? We're starting next week.
你的制片人有个好的打算
Your producer had a great idea.
准备办个舞会庆祝开拍
The greatest cocktail party ever to launch a movie.
那你知道在那么? 明天下午，午饭的时候
And you know where? - At the launch pad. Tomorrow afternoon.
电视台，广播台，还有国外记者呢
Radio, television, and all the foreign press.
来吧，贵都，我们要真正开始了
Come on, Guido, we're starting for real.
抓住他!
Catch him!
走，我们聊聊
Let's go. Walk!
我要回家了!
I want to go home.
这呢，他在这呢
Here, he's here.
贵都你去那?这没事了 别走啊
Guido, where are you going? It's over here.
贵都，今天一定是个伟大的时刻
Guido, I'm sure today will be a beautiful day.
我对你的构思非常好奇...
I'm really curious to finally hear the story...
你是不是过于自爱了，安瑟门先生?
Don't you take yourself a little too seriously, Mr. Anselmo?
别烦我，我自己可以走
Leave me alone, I can walk by myself.
祝你成功!
Good luck!
多特瑞，原来你在这儿
Dottore, here he is!
安静!
Calm down!
我们都等你这么长时间了，快冷场了啊
We've been waiting three days for you. It's winter already.
请安静!
Attention, please.
您认为色情也是艺术的分支么, 或者...
...do you think of pornography as an art form or...
或者色情会打破传统的...
...is pornography a more intense form of...
您为什么从来不拍爱情片?
...why don't you ever make a film about love?
我希望声明一下...
I wish to announce that...
明天...明天...
Tomorrow... tomorrow...
这部片子您在传达一种什么精神?
What do you think you can teach us?
您认为你的生活可以更加生动么?
Do you really think your life can be of any interest to others?
他要讲话了
He wants to say something.
快回答，说点什么啊，快
Answer, say something, go on.
什么都行，随便说也行
Anything at all! Say anything!
求求你了!
Do it for me!
我保证你...
I promise you...
...这部电影结束后，你想怎样都行
...this film. And afterward, what will you live on?
您是怎样看离婚的? 能谈谈么...
Are you for or against divorce? Tell me, frankly...
难道你要离婚么?
Is that your main problem?
您不想说，还是这只是您的借口?
That you can't communicate? Or is that just a pretext?
你的问题有点不太好!
Your questions betray a certain hostility.
我相信我走的路是正确的
I assure you my director is in great form...
我要怎么办?我该怎么办?
What should I do? What am I supposed to do?
他们该对他友好一点，因为...
...he should be treated with respect, because...
克诺斯雅，原谅我，如果我态度不好的话
Conocchia, forgive me if I treated you badly.
你是世上最伟大的人
You were wonderful, the best of them all.
充满了智慧和爱心
He ponders, considers, reflects.
请讲话!谈谈吧!
Speak! Answer!
我花钱就是要你做事的
I've paid for your confusion, your breakdown.
这几个月来我该做的都做了
For months I've been paying for everything.
现在退出的话我会杀了你
Quit this film and I'll ruin you.
他现在可以认我摆布了
He'll now be at your disposal.
新闻界一直...
The press always has been...
珂劳迪亚，你在那? 给我点鼓励吧，罗瑟拉?
Claudia, where are you? And your spirits, Rossella?
我该怎么做? 可以走么?
What should I do? Leave you? Disappear?
这次不用了
You will never be what you once were.
我还会是你的妻子么? 你什么时候可以和我结婚?
Will I ever be your wife? When will you truly marry me?
陆纱，你真的打算分手么?
Luisa, is it really true that you want a separation?
你舍得离开我么?
That you want to leave me?
我到最后还是接受不了
How can I go on like this 'til the end?
想想你老婆会怎么想?
...and what does your wife think?
在你的右边口袋里，多特里
It's in your right-hand pocket, Dottore.
够了，贵都
So long, Guido.
我放你右边口袋里了
I put it in your right-hand pocket.
谁都不可以带走. 布冯!
Nobody gets away with this. Buffoon!
滚出去，滚! 你个胆小鬼!
Out of there, out! You coward!
马上就好，马上! 让我想想怎么说
Just a minute, a little moment. I'm thinking of what to say.
我马上就来...很快的!
I'm coming... right away!
真是个多情的种子
Such an incurable romantic.
你要跑到那里去?
Where are you running, you low-life?
都拆了，伙计们 电影结束了
Take it all down, guys! The film is off.
两天内都拆了，马上开始行动
In two days it all has to be gone. Start right away.
都给我拆了，动手吧!
Tear it all down. Come on!
这就完了，多特里? 是的，十分感谢!
- Is that it, Dottore? - Yes, thanks.
大家保重了 下次再见吧
So long, guys. See you next time.
我们希望是
Let's hope so.
保重，赛乐!
So long, sailor.
你的决定是对的
You've made the right choice.
相信我，今天是个好的开始
Believe me, today is a good day for you.
这些决定不容易，我能理解
These are tough decisions, I know.
我们是对的，我说我们 是因为我一直在乎你的感受
But we intellectuals, and I say we because I consider you such,
任何时候都是一样的
must remain lucid to the bitter end.
生命本来就有好多疑惑
This life is so full of confusion already,
我们何必自寻烦恼呢
that there's no need to add chaos to chaos.
损失点钱其实是很正常的
Losing money is part of a producer's job.
我祝贺你 因为你没有办法
I congratulate you. You had no choice.
他却得到报应了
And he got what he deserved,
这么愚蠢的冲动，错误是必然的
for having joined such a frivolous venture so lightheartedly.
听我的，不用自责
Believe me, no need for remorse.
人要学会放弃
Destroying is better than creating
如果我们走的路是错的，就要学会放弃
when we're not creating those few, truly necessary things.
在这个世界上
But then is there anything so clear and right
没有什么事是绝对的
that it deserves to live in this world?
对他来说，电影失败了，也只是破财而已
For him, the wrong movie is only a financial matter.
对你来说，追求完美才更重要
But for you, at this point, it could have been the end.
放弃没什么不对，象古人一样
Better to quit and strew the ground with salt,
我们总有一天化作尘土，净化这个世界
as the ancients did, to purify the battlefields.
生命尽头，我们需要的是...
In the end what we need is...
纯洁的，透彻的世界
some hygiene, some cleanliness, disinfection.
如果我们玷污了画面，语言，声音
We're smothered by images, words and sounds
我们就没有权利生存，一点价值都没有了
that have no right to exist, coming from, and bound for, nothingness.
真的的艺术家，是不会象任何人索取什么的
Of any artist truly worth the name we should ask nothing
除了对艺术的追求，什么都可以不要!
except this act of faith: to learn silence.
还记得一本诗集上写着...
Do you remember Mallarme's homage to the white page?
等等，贵都
And Rimbaud... - Guido, wait!
把我当作朋友吧，忘了我的身份
...a poet, my friend, not a movie director. What was his finest poetry?
我们已经准备好了.
We're ready to begin.
那个作者现在已经停笔了，去非洲体验生活了
His refusal to continue writing and his departure for Africa.
恭喜了
Congratulations.
如果我们什么灵感都没有 就算拍了也一文不值
If we can't have everything, true perfection is nothingness.
原谅我的直言，可是批评家就要敢于说这话
Forgive me for quoting all the time. But we critics... do what we can.
我们的义务就是...排除一切不该有的错误
Our true mission is... sweeping away the thousands of miscarriages
每时每刻...都要...去寻找光明
that everyday... obscenely... try to come to the light.
你真的要放弃这部电影了么?
And you would actually dare leave behind you a whole film,
走了一半的路就要放弃了?
Iike a cripple who leaves behind his crooked footprint.
我真的不敢相信这是真的
Such a monstrous presumption to think
这么说别人不用受你的折磨了
that others could benefit from the squalid catalogue of your mistakes!
你这样会快乐么
And how do you benefit from stringing together
你难道不会后悔么?
the tattered pieces of your life?
你脑海里，有那些深爱着的人么
Your vague memories, the faces of people
还有他们的身影么?
that you were never able to love...
你做这个决定的时候不会哆嗦么
What is this sudden happiness that makes me tremble,
生命啊，给我力量吧!
giving me strength, life?
原谅我，亲爱的
Forgive me, sweet creatures.
我还是不能理解，不明白
I hadn't understood. I didn't know.
爱上你应该是很自然的事
It's so natural accepting you, loving you.
又这么简单
And so simple.
陆纱，我觉得自由了!
Luisa, I feel I've been freed.
什么事都很美好，有意义了!
Everything seems so good, so meaningful.
这世界开始真实了
Everything is true.
我希望可以释怀
I wish I could explain.
可不知道该怎样去
But I don't know how to.
事情又开始混沌了，象以前一样
So. Everything is confused again, as it was before.
光芒!
The lights!
这次，混沌的是...我
But this confusion is... me.
虽然不是我想要的，顺其自然吧
Not as I'd like to be, but as I am.
我再也不怕讲真话了
I'm not afraid anymore of telling the truth,
无论是我不理解的，正在寻找的，都不怕了
of the things I don't know, what I'm looking for and haven't found.
这样我才能活的更真实
This is the only way I can feel alive
我的眼睛可以诚实的看着你
and I can look into your faithful eyes without shame.
人生本就是个庆典
Life is a celebration.
我们要勇敢面对
Let's live it together!
这就是我要说的 陆纱， 对你也好，对别人也好
This is all I can say Luisa, to you or the others.
如果你还爱我，请接受我吧
Accept me for what I am, if you want me.
只有这样我们才能够相互接受
It's the only way we might be able to find each other.
我不知道你说的是不是对的
I don't know if what you said to me is right.
要是你帮我，我可以试试看
But I can try if you help me.
等一下，我就会让你们去做
Just a minute. I'll give you the go-ahead.
现在，都走到窗帘那
Now. Go to the curtain.
把它画下来
Draw it.
大家都下来
Everyone come down.
好好谈谈
Talk to each other.
妈妈
Mother.
闭嘴!我知道你要跟我说什么
Sgulp! I did understand what you wanted to say, you know.
你还是离不开我们的
That you can't do without us.
你明天什么时候给我电话? 好了，好了，现在排好队!
At what time will you call me tomorrow? - Fine, fine. Now join the line!
马里思
Maurice!
过来，快!别四处闲逛了.
Come, quickly! Stop fooling around.
每个人都手拉手一起转吧!
Everybody hold hands! Spread out! All together.
大师!
Maestro!
让我们跳舞吧
Let's all hold hands!
''八个半'' -= 剧终=-